<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fouretene sermons of Barnardine Ochyne, concernyng the predestinacion and eleccion of god: very expediente to the settynge forth of hys glorye among hys creatures. Translated out of Italian in to oure natyve younge by A.C.</title>
            <author>Ochino, Bernardino, 1487-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104170</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839909</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 121:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fouretene sermons of Barnardine Ochyne, concernyng the predestinacion and eleccion of god: very expediente to the settynge forth of hys glorye among hys creatures. Translated out of Italian in to oure natyve younge by A.C.</title>
                  <author>Ochino, Bernardino, 1487-1564.</author>
                  <author>Bacon, Anne Cooke, Lady, 1528?-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1286] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Day dwellynge ouer Aldersgate, [and] Wylliam Seres, dwellyng in Peter Colledge. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1551?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by Lady Anne Bacon.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H (H8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4370:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4370:1"/>
            <p>¶ Fouretene Sermons of Barnardine Ochyne, concernyng the predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion and eleccion of god: very expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente to the ſettynge forth of hys glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye among hys creatures. Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of Italian in to oure natyue tounge by. A.C.</p>
            <p>☞It is good to hyde the Kinges ſecretes, but to decleare and prayſe the workes of god, it is an honorable thing. Co. xij.</p>
            <p>☞I wyl ſaye to the north, let go and to the ſouthe, kepe not backe: but brynge my Sonnes and my Daughters from the endes of the world, namely all thoſe that be called after my name. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue I created, faſhyoned, and made for mine honor. Eſa. xliii.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4370:2"/>
            <head>The titles of the Chaptres,</head>
            <list>
               <item>i. Whether predeſtinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſpoken, or thought.</item>
               <item>ii. How excelent our election is.</item>
               <item>iij. If we maye knowe in thys preſente lyfe whether we be of the electe and in the grace or fauour of God or not.</item>
               <item>iiij. Whether it be good to knowe or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that we are elect.</item>
               <item>v. Whether it be neceſſarye to ſaluacion to beleue that we are elect or no.</item>
               <item>vi. If it be good to knowe wherefore God hath elect ſum and ſume reprobate.</item>
               <item>vij. Of the diuers effectes it worketh in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beleue that our election is al in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God &amp; that of him only it dependeth</item>
               <item>viij. Howe it ought to be anſwered to them which lamente that God hath create theym forſeyng their damnacion.</item>
               <item>ix. Wherefore God hath elected vs.</item>
               <item>x. Whether the elect can be damned or not</item>
               <item>xi. Whether god do aggrauat, harden, and blynd the hartes of men &amp; in what maner.</item>
               <item>xij. Howe god doth dyſpence hys grace.</item>
               <item>xiij. If man haue liberty or not, and in what maner.</item>
               <item>xiiij. Of the effect wrought by the ſpirite of God when it entreth the ſoule.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4370:2"/>
            <head>☞To the Chriſten. Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEn theſe tranſlated ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons of the famous Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardine were come to myne hand, Ientyll Reader, I th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ought it mete to publyſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ende ſo Godly Apoſtolyke doctryne ſhould not be priuate to thoſe onely whych vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the Italian toung, ſynce thorow the honeſt trauel of a wel occupied Ien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telwoman, and verteouſe meyden they ſpeake in Englyſhe: whoſe ſhamfaſtnes would rather haue ſuppreſt theym, had not I to whoſe handes they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted halfe agaynſt hyr wyll put them fourth, biddyng them bluſh that deſerue blame: for thys of her parte I dare ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affyrme craueth perpetual praiſe and if any prety pryckemydantes ſhal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to ſpy amote in thys godly labour (as I doughte not but the niſytes wyl) ſeynge it is meeter for Docters of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitye to meddle wyth ſuch matters the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Meydens, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber howe woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they waſt their tyme the one part in
<pb facs="tcp:4370:3"/>
pryckeynge and trymmynge to vayne hethennyſhe oſtentacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in deuiſyng newe faſhyons of apparel, to whome if in their glaſſe appered the fowle fautes of their fylthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions as playnely as the defautes of theyr forſayde faces, I doubt much whether thei wold delight to tooſe therin ſo often as thei do: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part ſpeakyng in prynt lyke para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes wyth ſolemne countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, debate matters of importau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; graue weight, as though the ordre of realmes appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to them, or els warbling wordes of ſcripture in all their doynges, deface the thyng they moſt bable of. But I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the (Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reader) wyth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to reade, &amp; in the equal balaunce of Scripture to way theſe learned &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſermons, whych thou ſhalt fynde (I dout not) of iuſt weyght with the ſacred word of God: I forbare to prayſe them, leſt I ſhould ſay to lytle, defend them I nede not the authour lyuinge and here amongeſt vs: a man whoſe lyfe wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wordes were a ſuffyciente protecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to hys worcke. If oughte be erred in the tranſlacion, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber it is a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s yea, a Ientyl woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly are wonted to lyue Idelly, a maidens y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer gaddid farder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir fathers houſe to learne the language. Fare wel &amp; vſe hyr labor to the amendement of thy life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4370:3"/>
            <head>¶To the right worſhypful and worthyly beloued Mother, the Lady. F. hyr humble Daughter wyſheth encreaſe of ſpirituall knowledge, with ful frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the fruites thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the Orygynal of what ſo euer is, or may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni good vſe in me, hath frelye proceded (thoughe as the miniſter of GOD) of youre La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhypes mere carefull, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly goodnes, as well in procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge all thynges thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeynge, as in youre many, and moſt Godly exhortacyons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in amonge the reſt it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:4370:4"/>
you, ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to reproue my vaine ſtudye in the Italyan tonge, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting the ſede thereof, to haue bene ſowen in barayne, vnfruitful grounde (ſyns God thereby is no whytte magnifyed) I haue at the laſt, perceiued it my duty to proue howe muche the vnderſtandynge of youre wyll, could worcke in me towardes the accomplyſhynge of the ſame. And for that I haue wel knowen your chyfe delight, to reſt in the deſtroynge of man hys glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and exaltynge wholy the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God: whych may not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les we acknowledge that he, doth fore ſe and determyne from wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out begynnynge, al thynges, and cannot alter or rewarde after our deſerued worckes, but remayne ſtedefaſte, accordynge to hys im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable wyll, I haue taken in hande to dedicate vnto youre La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip this ſmale number of Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons
<pb facs="tcp:4370:4"/>
(for the excele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fruit ſake in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conteined, proceding from the happy ſpirit of the ſantified Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardyne, which treat of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> election and predeſtinacion of God, wyth the reſt (although not of the ſelfe title) a perteynig to the ſame effect to the end it might appere, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſo many worthy ſentences touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, haue not vtterly ben w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſome note in my weake me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, &amp; al be it, they be not done in ſuch perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the dignitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter doth requyre: yet I truſt &amp; know, ye wil accept y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble wil of the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, not weghing ſo much the excelnecy of the tranſlacion, al thoughe of ryghte it oughte to be ſuch as ſhould not by the groſnes therof depriue the aucthor of his worthynes. But not meanynge to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reache, to his hygh ſtyle of thealogie, and fearyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, leaſt in enterpriſynge to ſette
<pb facs="tcp:4370:5"/>
forth the bryghtnes of hys elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, I ſhuld manyfeſt my ſelfe vnapte, to attaine vnto the loweſt degre therof. I deſcend therefore, to the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of myne own debilitye. Only requiring, that it may pleaſe youre Ladyſhippe to vouchſafe that thys my ſmal la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor may be alowed at your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des vnder whoſe proteccion only it is commited wyth humble re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence, as yeldyng ſome parte of the fruite of your Motherly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monicions, in this my wyllinge ſeruyce.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>☞Your Ladyſhyppes Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moſt boundenly obedient. A.C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4370:5"/>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>¶Whether Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion oughte to be wrytten, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or thought: the fyrſte Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Her are ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny that wold not here prede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinacion ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, nor once named, and if they might let it, it ſhuld ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and that is becauſe it ſemeth them to gyue offence, and ingender co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion amonge the people. ☞I cannot denye, that many curiouſe per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons wyth theyr darcke natural lyght (wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſe thinges ſupernatural that cannot be ſene but by fayth) do fal into thouſandes of errours, and cauſe other to fall into the lyke. Al that they maye imagine by force of wyt, pleaſynge to theyr owne corrupt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (of that hyghe ſecrete) they thyncke it to be true, wythout other teſtimonye of holye ſcripture. And thereby haue intangled their braynes, darkened theyr myndes, and offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded theyr conſciences. Curyoſytye is an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſatiable
<pb facs="tcp:4370:6"/>
beaſt, it would pearce thorowe all thynges, and yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not get out of his darke and intricate laborinthes, nor once lyft vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the heade to diuyne ſecrettes. And if we ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffer our ſelues to be guyded of it (in thinges ſpeciallye ſupernaturall, neyther wyll it at any tyme be ſatiſfied, nor we ſhall neuer perceyue the trueth. For immedialye after it paſſeth the borders of the natural lyghte, it goeth alwayes blynded and at aduentur. Therefore it muſt be put a ſyde and (bryng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge hys vnſaciable wyl to an ende) walke by fayth to deuyne ſecrettes honoryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wythout further dyſcuſſion. And if we be prouoked to ſerch them out by the wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of humayne wyt: we oughte to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that,<note place="margin">Prou. xxv.</note> which is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: He that ſearcheth the maieſtie of God, ſhalbe ouercome with the glorye thereof. It is our offyce, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with as much as God hath vouchafed to open vnto vs in the ſacred Scripturs, in the whych, he hath gyuen vs lyght ſufficy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently. But note, that as it is euel to be curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe in wyllynge to knowe more then that whych in the ſcripture is conteyned, and to vs reueled, ſo is it alſo euell, to be ignorant and not to ſeke to vnderſtande as much as therin is: for that in them ſpeaketh the holy goſt who gyueth none offence but edifyeth
<pb facs="tcp:4370:6"/>
In them is writen nothyng pernicious, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, or vayne, but only commodious and neceſſary. Neyther ought it to offende any man, when it is ſpoken of, in the maner that Paulle ſpeaketh of it. And we neyther maye nor ought to be more circumſpecte in ſpeakyng therof then Paule, ye then God,<note place="margin">Gala. ii.</note> that ſpeake in hym. Thynckeſt thou haplye that Paule (yea rather Chriſte that lyued in hym, and moued hym to wryte) dyd erre in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wrote of it in ſuche ſort, as he dyd? The holy goſt would neuer haue gyuen vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge thereof in the holy ſcripture, if it had bene euell. Thou wylt ſaye, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge of it in ſuch maner as Paule wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: gyueth offence, as it is euidente. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that Chriſt crucified, was an offence to the Hebrues:<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> therfore the apoſtles dyd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to preache it. The goſpel ſemed folyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the wyſe of the world: And therefore it ſhoulde not be taughte. The trueth is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſaunt to the falſe chriſtians, they fynde offence of the goſpell, and Iuſtificacion by Chriſte, ſhoulde it then be kepte in ſilence? Wherfore wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that we holde oure peace of that thyng whych Paule writteth? How can the wordes of the holy goſt offend, that haue bene pronounced and wrytten onelye for oure ſaluacion? If thou be offended ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyth,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:7"/>
it is not becauſe it gyueth the occacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but for that thou takeſt it without any gift. Neyther oughte the thereof to ceaſſe, more then the Apoſtles left preachynge, thoughe many were offendyd therwyth. Thou wilt ſaye, to preache the Goſpell is neceſſarye. Wherfore that oughte not to be lefte for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: and I ſaye that predeſtinacion is a great parte of the Goſpell. Wouldeſt thou not thynke thys a goodlye Goſpell or glad tydynges, that God from wythout begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, had by his mere grace, and by Chriſt crucified, elected vs to be hys children, and that we be ſuer in hys handes? It is a thing moſte neceſſarye, to preache thoſe good ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, in the whyche ther is dyſcouered vnto vs the exceadynge goodnes of God, that aboue all other thynges doeth moue vs to be ennamored of hym, And he that is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded wyth predeſtinacion, preached in the maner it ought to be, is alſo offended wyth the Goſpell. Knoweſt thou (that whyche in dede doth hurt, althoughe it appeare not to the blynde and frantyke worlde) that anye man preacheth it after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humaine doctrine? But it maye be thou wylt ſaye, let vs come therefore to the particulars. Doeth it not ſeme to the, offence, to preach that god hath electe ſome and not other ſome? He that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:4370:7"/>
theſe wordes, wyll thyncke God to be parciall. I anſwere and fyrſt I ſaye, that god cannot erre; nor wyll other wyſe then iuſtly: Yea hys wyll is ſo ryghte, that as he alway wylleth any thyng, it is euen by that wyllynge moſt iuſt. Therefore none ſhould be offended wyth hys workes, for as much as he maye dyſpoſe vs after his owne way, and ſhewe hys pleaſure vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs more then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> potter vpon hys pottes: and al wyth iuſtice &amp; equite. For what bond hath god with vs? Moreouer,<note place="margin">Rom. ix.</note> by the ſynnes of Adam we are al loſt, and he myghte iuſtlye damne vs al, but he ſaueth as manye as hym pleaſeth: and yet we complayne, where we are not worthy by ſufferyng al puniſhmente to ſet furthe the bryghtnes of hys glorye. Yea it oughte to be preached that God hath elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome, and not other ſome: for to ſmite to the earth the wiſdome of man and to make him al humble and ſubiecte to God Now,<note place="margin">Rom. iii.</note> is it not neceſſary to be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we ſhal not all be ſaued, and that many ſhalbe dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned? And conſequentlye God hath many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte and manye reiected. Thou wouldeſt ſaye, thys ſhoulde gyue no occacion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, if it were preached, that thoſe that he hath choſen, are choſen for ther merites, and thoſe he hath forſaken, are forſaken for
<pb facs="tcp:4370:8"/>
theyr wickednes but thei ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe he hath elect, are elected by hys mere grace, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes, and that oure election and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon dependeth hollye vpon God. And thys gyueth the offence to the worlde.<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. If this be offence, Paule hath gyuen it him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Rom. ix.</note> becauſe it is the doctrine of him ye rather of the holy goſt. Wylt thou be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffendyd,<note place="margin">Rom. viii. Ephe. i.</note> if Paule magnifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fre mercy, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng God hath elected vs to the laud of hys glory, as he wrytteth? We cannot magnify it ſufficiently. But thou feareſt it ſhould be lauded and exalted to much. If it were told the thou were elected by they workes, then would I thou ſhuldeſt be offended, for that it would make the beleue thy ſaluacion, to depend vpon thy ſelfe, wherby thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be begiled.<note place="margin">Oſe. xiii.</note> For of thy ſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth thy damnacion, and of God thy ſaluacion. Yea as often as thou thynckeſt thy ſaluacion in anye parte to depende vpon thy ſelfe, it dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the, eyther to dyſpare or to be exallted in preſumpcyon. And in ſuch caſe thou can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt neuer put in God all thy hope, nor all thy loue, neyther haue perfect quyetnes of mynde, nor of conſcyence. Thou wouldeſt ſay, that who ſo knoweth that God aboue is reſolued vpon all thynges: waxeth colde in well doyng, and ſayth, what nede I more
<pb facs="tcp:4370:8"/>
to trauayle, God hath immutably determi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and reſolued all that is to be, I maye paſſe my tyme in pleaſure, for if I be elect I ſhall euery way be ſaued, And if I be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, I cannot ſaue my ſelfe, thoughe I neuer ceaſed to axe it, on my bare knees. Thou perceyueſt not, that he which ſayeth ſo, doth dyſcouer hym ſelfe ſhewynge that he neuer dyd good workes, &amp; yet he would hys ſaluacion ſhould depend vpon hym ſelfe. Thys ſort of men, if they do any good (as they call it) it is to wyn heauen, and not for the glory of God. Therefore if they ſhould beleue that theyr ſaluacion and elec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon dyd not come of them ſelues (as men that were not mouyd wyth the zeale of the honor of God) they would dwell in Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yea, gyue theym ſelues to lyue lycenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and vngodly, wythout reſpecte of the dyſhonour of God, they are fearefull Seruauntes and hirelynges, and not ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, they ſerue theym ſelues and not God, and theym ſelues they worſhyp. The electe do neuer become could, but are the more feruent, by hearynge that their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and ſaluacion is onely in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of God, they know by fayeth, that the lorde louyth theim ſo much (ſpecially ſynce Chriſte hath dyed for theym on the croſſe)
<pb facs="tcp:4370:9"/>
that they are ſuer of theyr ſaluacion. Yea they feale ſomuch the goodnes of God in Chriſte, and by Chriſt, that if it weare poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble (whyle that ſpirituall felyng dyd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in them) that they cold beleue them ſelues to be reprobate (for as muche as by thys,<note place="margin">i. Re. xxviii.</note> god is no leſſe good) they would not a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny thyng the leſſe loue hym, or trauayle to honor hym, euen as Saule ceſſed not moſt coragyouſly to fyght for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of God, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though it was foretould him of hys death. The elect vnderſtand in ſpirit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are the children of God. Wherfore they are forced by ſtrength of loue &amp; learne to haue condici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient to theyr ſo hye eſtate:<note place="margin">Hebru. xii.</note> &amp; are al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo aſhamed to do a wycked worke, not ſeme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li or ſetting to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bewty of their dignitie. And ſo much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, do they feare ſo ſinne, by how much more they know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god doeth in thys preſent lyfe, punyſhe hys le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the baſterdes. If and aſtrologyer ſhould tell an ambycious man that he ſhoulde be pope, althoughe he dyd put vndouted truſt there in, yet for all that he woulde not be Idell, but would ſet furth hym ſelfe by all meanes po yble to come to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dignitie. Euen ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of god, the ſuerer thei are of their eleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more they vnderſtande the greate goodnes
<pb facs="tcp:4370:9"/>
of God. They are alwaies forced therfore, more &amp; more by good workes, to make cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to them ſelues the knowledge of their eleccion.<note place="margin">ii. Pet. i.</note> Euery one wyll trauayle for the thinges of the world. There is none that ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth I wyl be Idle, or I wyll not eate, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes I ſhall lyue, and be rych and happy in the thinges of the world, if God haue for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſene and determined it? Only in thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges perteining to the ſoule, predeſtinacion hindreth them by making it a ſhylde to their wicked life. But know thou that thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of ſuch a benefit take occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to become worſe, (though already with their hart they dyd the ſame thinges and wolde haue done it in worke if they had thought them ſure of their ſaluacion) ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. xi.</note> &amp; not to feele in Chriſt the great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God. Sathan is he that being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the ſimilitude of an Aungel of lyght, trauayleth to perſwade that our elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion dependeth vpon vs. This was the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Pelagius: and the Pelagians are they that be offended with this great mercy of God: they thinke that God neither may, can, or wyll do other then reaſon. Then of force muſte it be good to be preached, to the end it may be knowen,<note place="margin">Eſa. lv.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the time is already come of the couenaunt and promiſed peace
<pb facs="tcp:4370:10"/>
that he which hath eares to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Math. xiii.</note> may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepe of chriſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heare their paſtour. It is alſo good to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that be not hyd but declared, which (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of God &amp; for oure profite) is written therof in holye ſcripture:<note place="margin">Ihon. x.</note> &amp;, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpecial cure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath of vs, may be know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en, &amp; how we ſhuld ſerue him frely as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; not as timerous ſeruauntes &amp; hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges. Yea &amp; that it may be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that God (being abſolutelie the Lord) may do al that he wil, &amp; what he willeth is iuſt, &amp; to the end alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be diſcouered to vs, in ſuperabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maner, his fre mercy, &amp; that it may be ſene how we are preuented by innumerable benitites, &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is only vanitie,<note place="margin">Pſal. xxxviii.</note> &amp; euer an vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruaunt. Paradiſe we litle worth if with our workes wee could wyn it but it is the inheritaunce of ſonnes, &amp; not a reward for ſeruauntes. I wolde knowe what men wold ſaye, if God ſhuld ſaye to them: chuſe whether ye wyl ſtand to my election and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which I haue determined of you, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anulling (if this wer poſſible) al that I haue purpoſed to do with you, ſhuld reſolue me holi to put it in you, And to ſaue you if ye do good workes and perſeuer in them, &amp; if you do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me you. I am ſure then
<pb facs="tcp:4370:10"/>
men ſhuld know their owne frailtye, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce &amp; malice. And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other partie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of God, &amp; remit it holy to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, &amp; much more if thei loued him, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter glory to god, yea &amp; alſo for their own pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, for it ſhuld neuer be done, if it depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. And therfore for euery reſpect, euery one ſhuld ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to gods determinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if it were for nothinge but to do honour to him. It is a thing more magni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; to god more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, to geue para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice by fre mercie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if he ſhuld ſel it: his li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beralitie is therby moſt diſcouered. Then, for his greater glory I would alwaies ſay, god hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me this. And alſo for mi own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wheras now I hold my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſure (for that I know it ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god) I wold thinke me da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, or at the leaſt preſuming on my ſelf, ſtand in dout, if in the leaſt point it did depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, bicauſe god inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parably doth loue me more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do my ſelf. Yea, I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt enemy &amp; trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to my ſelf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be. Therfore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought bi euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion doth ſtande in the hande of god: yea in taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole cure of vs, he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs moſt dere loue, he hath willed vs to be ſure of it. And therefore he woulde not truſte to vs, knowinge wee are ſo vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that if we had paradiſe in our handes,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:11"/>
we ſhould let it fal to therth where now we are ſure knowinge that al our ſinnes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not let the diuine eleccion, neither quench or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhe the diuine charitie. Yea, hereof our ſinnes toke occaſion to be ſhewed with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of more loue.<note place="margin">Roma. v.</note> We are not by this inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to more Idlenes, nor to watche when we ſhall haue Manna from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither to be wickedly occupyed, but we are drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and moued ſo much more to loue him, as he is diſcouered to vs by more bountie and cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie. But thoſe that are not by Chriſte rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, are of ſo baſe &amp; vyle a mind through ſinne, that they can not thinke God to be ſo liberall as to geue heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. But they ought at the leaſte to thinke, that to bye it the bloud of Chriſt is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without adioyning therto their workes to boote: which ſurely are rych iuels to be min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gled with his God is ſo fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke, that he hath geuen vs Chriſt,<note place="margin">Roma. viii.</note> and in him al thinges, and canſt not thou thinke he hath geuen the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? It is alſo our greater glorie, that God hath loued vs ſomuche, that his owne ſelfe hath wylled to take the care &amp; charge of our ſaluation. And ſo to that ende hath wylled his only ſonne to die vpon the croſſe, ſo that if with all our trauaile we might enter into heauen by our ſelues: the glorie only of the
<pb facs="tcp:4370:11"/>
croſſe is a far greater glory then any other which by our ſelues we could attaine. Yea, there is no other trew glory, then to glorie to be ſo much loued of God, that he hath to ſaue vs, put his ſonne vpon the croſſe. He may not dwel in his owne loue, that willeth to be happy, and only glory in God. If we myght glorye of ourſelues, we ſhould haue wherof to waxe proude and prefer our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues afore oure brethern, where otherwyſe we ſhould haue occaſion to be humble, and geue to God all honoure and glorye as to him it apperteineth.<note place="margin">i. Timo. i.</note> And further ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be by grace elected, ſaued ſonnes of God, heyres and ſure therof, not only becauſe ther remaineth no more to get (God in Chriſt hauing geuen them all) but alſo by the great vnderſtanding they haue of the goodnes of the Lord: they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to worke as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the glori of their father, and not for their owne gaine, and ſo alſo ſure of their ſaluacion, with Chriſt they turne them with al their force, to ſeke the ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion of their brother: they demaund alſo grace with a bolder ſpirite and confidence, ſence they axe it not for their owne lucre, but for he honor of God,<note place="margin">Epheſi. i. Rom. vi. Pſal. xxxii.</note> and to his laude and gloy: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the worldes to come, may be ſene &amp; abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant riches of his fre mercy.
<pb facs="tcp:4370:12"/>
Moreouer ſuch hope to be hard for that thei thinke not to deſerue grace,<note place="margin">Rom. iiii. Gala. iii. ii. Cor iii. Ioh. iii.</note> neither put their truſt in their owne workes, but in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, being inſpired and moued ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to by the holy goſt. Suche alſo as feele that our ſaluacion dependeth not vpon vs, but oure damnacion, and that it ſtandeth who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in the hande of God: are forced to turne their backes to them ſelues, and theyr faces to God: Where as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary belefe, wold make the contrary operacion, they would withdraw them from God, and ſeke to reſte with hope in them ſelues: alſo if God had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected vs with this condicion:<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> If we wolde do well, we ſhould be vnder the lawe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Paul, neither we ſhould be ſaued, for the law ſaueth not but worketh wrathe, and is the miniſter of curſing and damnaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Let him therfore that luſteth haue Chriſt for his iudge, for I wyl none of him, but as a ſauiour. If our eleccion by fre mercy dyd harme vs, he wold not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue elected vs ſo. But note them that thinke to haue theyr eleccion in their owne handes, &amp; thou ſhalt ſe that thei are in their owne loue and truſt, preſumtuous, and full of vyce: and yet for all thys they be ſo blynd and arrogant, that they wyll haue heauen by iuſtice.</p>
               <p>But let vs praye to the Lorde that he
<pb facs="tcp:4370:12"/>
gyue them knowledge to the ende they may render to God all laude, honour, and glorye, throughe oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <head>¶Howe excellent oure eleccion is, the ſeconde Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aul magnifieth our eleccion, fyrſte in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe that hath elected vs, ſayinge: Wee are elected neyther by man nor Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, but by God: Hyer ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not he go. Then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge hym that elected vs, oure eleccion is moſte excellente. And lykewyſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the circumſtaunce of tyme, although aboue there is properlye no courſe of tyme. He elected vs (as Paull wryteth) before the conſtitucion of the worlde:<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> meanynge from wythoute begynnynge, ſooner coulde he not electe vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:13"/>And moreouer he ſaythe, that he elected vs which are moſt baſe, moſt vile, moſt abiect, wormes in compariſon of him. Bi the ſinne of Adam we were all defyled, infected, in firme, frayle, blynd, malingnaunte, full of venim, contrari to god, enemies and rebels: ſo that a thinge more miſerable coulde not haue binne choſen. Paule doth alſo magni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye oure election, in reſpect of the dignittie, to the whiche we are elected, and ſayth, he hath not choſen vs to be hys ſeruauntes or frendes, but to be hys children, nothyng to god can be more nyghe, entire and dere, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his children, nether is it poſſible to imagine a greater dignitie. It doth include al other vertues and goodnes, it is ſo hyghe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent. Being then elected from ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an eſtate, to be the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of god. He hath alſo choſen vs to be the brethren of Chriſte &amp; therby with him coheires of god:<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> yea the worlde is oures? Chryſt with al his gyftes, al that is the fathers is the ſonnes, therfore al is ours y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is gods, whoſe goodes we mai dyſpoſe as children their fathers. And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſhould ſhame to be the ſonnes of god, not hauing the maners, graces, and vertues conueient to ſuche a dygnitie, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not onlye oure heauenlye father, hath choſen vs to be his ſonnes, but hath bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:4370:13"/>
vs, not wyth wordes onlye, but wyth effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, not as Iſaac bleſſed Iacob or Eſau, but wyth all ſpirituall bleſſ nge in thinges celeſtiall. And ſo accordyng to Paule,<note place="margin">Ephe. i. Collo. i</note> hathe made vs mete to be partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of lyght, &amp; delyuering vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of darkenes, hath ledde vs into the kinge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of his beloued ſonne: God then with oute beginninge did determyne to iuſtifye, glorifye, and magnyfie thoſe that he hadde elect, and euen ſo he hath done:<note place="margin">Rom. vii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as Paule wryteth, who alſo exaltyth our election for that cauſe, ſainge: that it was not our good worckes, which God forſawe wythout be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, that were the cauſe of our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but he choſe vs by mere mercie, accordynge to the decreed purpoſe of his owne wyll, to the laud and glorie of his mercie, we were not then choſen bycauſe we were Holye, but bycauſe we ſhoulde be holly bi his elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to ſhewe in the worldes to come,<note place="margin">Ephe. i &amp; .ii</note> the abundante riches of his grace. Paule alſo ſhewyth the worthines of our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by reſpecte of the dignitie of the perſon by whoſe meanes we are choſen, and ſaithe, he hath willed, that betwene vs and him there ſhuld be one mediator, nether he wold it to be an angel, but Chriſt the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God.<note place="margin">i. Timo. ii. Ephe. i.</note> He meaneth not onlie a mediator with wordes,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:14"/>
but with his owne bloud, and death Paul doth exalt our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end. For bicauſe he hathe elected vs for his ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to the end we may taſte (not only in the life to come, but alſo in this preſent) things ſo highe, happye, riche, and pure, that the eie hath not ſene, nor the eare hath not hard, nor into the hart of man (being carnal) hath at any tyme entred,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii.</note> he hath then elected vs, to the ende (that regenerate bi Chriſte Ieſu) we ſhuld walke to God by good workes,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be hollie and inreprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible, before his preſence. Our election is alſo excellente by the ſuertye therof, for that the elect are in the handes of God.<note place="margin">Ephe i. Ihon. x.</note> Therefore ſhal not thei periſhe as Chriſt ſayth, yea they can not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, euen as they can not bee pluckte oute of his handes. Therfore oure election is moſte happye, ſo that nothynge oughte ſo muche to bee reioyſed in, as to bee the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and choſen of God. Therfore it is read, the diſciples returning to Chriſt, and reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge with greate gladnes, that euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray deuelles were ſubiecte to them,<note place="margin">Luke. x.</note> Chryſt amonge the reſte of wordes, bade them thei ſhulde not reioyſe of the ſubiection of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uels, but that their names were written in heauen: by which wordes, he did ſhew, that we ought to make a ſinguler Ioye of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:14"/>
for that includeth, and bringeth with it the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of all our wealth, ſince then that our eleccion is ſo excellent, ryche, ſure, and hapy. Let vs pray to God to geue vs lighte and grace, to perceyue it, to thende, that taſtinge in it (with the ſpirite) the myghtie goodnes of God, we may re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der him al laude, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor: and glorye, by Ieſu Chriſte our Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <head>¶If wee maie knowe in this preſent lyfe,<note place="margin">This hole ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon muſt be warely red, &amp; wel vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, or els it muſt be taken but as perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not as do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine,</note> whether we be in the grace of God, &amp; one of his electe or not, and in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the thyrd Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not to be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God ſeeth all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſpecially his legitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf hath choſen them to that dignitie.<note place="margin">ii. Timo. ii Ephe. i.</note> Chriſt alſo knoweth, &amp; knew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaies, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſence his father had geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him for that he ſhulde be theyr gouernor, ſhepherd, &amp; brother, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhuld ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his own death: he knew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; doth know his ſhepe euen as himſelfe ſayd,<note place="margin">Ihon. vii. Iohn. vi.</note> yea fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning he knew who ſhould beleue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:15"/>But it is not now conuenient,<note place="margin">Math. xiii.</note> that we may or can deſerue diſtinctlye, the elect from the reprobate, to the ende we may be more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in exerciſinge charite, with all men, as if they were brethern with vs in Chriſt, the which we would not do towarde the repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate if we knewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtinctly: But in the ende, the tares ſhalbe ſeperate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the good wheat: none then beinge in this preſent lyfe knoweth certenly of his neighbour, if he be of the elect or not, nor alſo whether he be in the fauour of God: we may only haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of an obſcure, confuſed, vncertein, and fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng knowledge by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward lyfe and workes, of whom Chriſt ſpeaking, ſayd.<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> Ye ſhall knowe them by their fruites. But foraſmuch as we ſee not the hertes of men,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii. Luke. xvi.</note> which often times (although within they are vngodly and abhominacion it ſelfe in the ſyght of God, neuertheles coueringe them with the veyle of hipocriſie maſkinge therin) they apeare to be ſainctes. Therfore without ſpeciall oracle, we can haue no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine knowledge therof. But I ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery elect, whyle he is in this preſent lyfe, beinge come to the yeres of diſcreſſion, maye, and ought to know it of himſelf, not by natural lyght (by meanes wherof thinges ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ural can not be perceiued, as the excellent
<pb facs="tcp:4370:15"/>
diuine wyl toward vs) but by faithe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other ſpeciall priuilege. And this not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hauing reſpect to them ſelues, where is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſene but worthy damnacion, neither with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideringe or beholding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in God without Chriſte, for in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> caſe he muſt ſhew himſelf to vs a iuſt iudgeful of wrath: then we neither ſe our ſelues his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, nor in fauour. But with liuely fayth beholding both our ſelues, &amp; God in Chriſt, we ſe our ſelues to be in the fauour of god, &amp; his elect ſonnes, &amp; god to be pacified with vs in loue and our only father. Such then as liuely be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath died vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, haue the holy goſt within them, &amp; are in the fauour of God, bicauſe that faith doth puri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie the hert.<note place="margin">
                     <p>This muſte be warly red and well vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or it is not true. But if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> vnderſtande what it is to beleue in chriſt with a liuely faith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no daunger at al.</p>
                     <p>i. Iho. v.</p>
                  </note> And further I ſay, that al they which in this preſent lyfe to beleue liuely in Chriſt (yea were it for a moment of time) ſhalbe ſauid. Thei are electe and ſonnes of God, and may be ſuer and certeine, of their ſaluation. And that this is true, the wordes of ſainte Ihon ought to ſuffiſe, which ſaith, that he is the ſonne of God, therfore electe and ſauid, who ſo beleueth Ieſu Chriſte to be the ſonne of God. And alſo Chriſt ſayde who ſo beleueth in me hath lyfe euerlaſting neuertheleſſe it may clearlye be prouid that none beleueth liuelye in Chryſte, but he that
<pb facs="tcp:4370:16"/>
but he that beleueth Chryſt to be wholy his rightwiſenes and that he is ſaued thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye by him, and he that ſeethe this wyth ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding hauing no reſpect to him ſelfe nor his workes, but only to the goodnes of God diſcouered in Chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe, can not by any meanes be diſcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light which he hath to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauor of God, elect to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not grow but onlye of the bounty of God, conſidered in Chriſt, wherof can ſpring no falſe nor de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceitfull knowledge. Full well may he be be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giled and ſhalbe, that doth behold his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and by them thinketh that he is in the fauour of God and his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. But ſeing him ſelfe in Chryſt ſaued, choſen &amp; in the fauour of God, it muſte nedes be ſaid, that he ſeeth the truthe, and that which is once trewe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were but for the twincke of an eie muſt be ſaide to be euer true, he then whiche beleueth in Chriſte, were it but a minute of an houre, in perceyuing of him ſelfe elect by Chriſt, ſeeth that which is true, therfore ſhall it euer be true, that he is one of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimat ſonnes of God, ſo that the ſame his faythe, be not in anye maner founded vpon him ſelf, nor his own worckes, but in chriſt, and the diuine excellence, and that it be not a certeine trifleinge, lighte, baren and deade
<pb facs="tcp:4370:16"/>
opinion, but a liuely faithe. It muſt be ſaid then that Iudas had neuer perfect faith, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was elect to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, although he was choſen to the apoſtelſhippe, and the like ſay I of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reprobate: al ſuch then as haue had at anie time liuely belefe to be ſaued bi chriſt may be ſuer of their ſaluation. And ſo alſo they, whiche haue once at the leaſt bene per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectely geuen to God, and committed to his gouernaunce, vpon the couenaunte, that he ſhall ſerue himſelfe of them accordynge to his owne purpoſe, and with truſte that by Chriſt and his mere goodnes he hath accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted them for his owne, they maye alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that they are ſaued, bycauſe that he ſhal be no leſſe God to them, then thei ſhal be promiſed of him.</p>
               <p>Therfore hauing had in that couenaunte lyuely faythe,<note place="margin">This is not ſpoken to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that it is poſſible for gods elect to be wholy geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſynne. but if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet ſhould they recouer that peſtilence.</note> that God wyll forgeue them as his Chyldren, in ſuche ſorte, that he wyl conducte them to ſaluacion, althoughe they (as muche as lyeth in them) were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie prompte to all euyll: yet is it neceſſary to ſaye, that ſence God hathe taken them for his (as they knowe by the lyuely faythe that they haue hadde thereof) that they ſhall ouercome that wyckednes and haue honoure thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:17"/>For hys goodnes paſſithe theyr euelnes he wold not haue inſpired them to gyue them ſelfes, if from withoute beginning, he had not elected them and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his owne. Some peraduenture will ſaye, if we were onlye ones ſuer to haue bene for a litle time in the fauour of God, to haue had his ſpirit in vs, and liuely faith in him, that we did beleue ſuerlye to be his elect: yet we knowe not if it haue bene a perfect fayth or not, we feare it to haue bene a certeine cold opinion and leſte we were begiled in beleuing to be in gods fouor and elected of him. I anſwer that this is an euidente ſigne, that ye haue neuer had hitherto liuelye faith and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of chriſte. For as it is vnpoſſible to haue fyre within the breſt and not fele it, ſo is it impoſſible to haue in the hart chriſt, the holye ghoſte, ardent charitie and the fierye lighte of faythe, and not to perceiue it, and this is, for that his lighte is ſo clere and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuous, that not only it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſe, and liuelie to fele with the ſpirit, that chriſt is deade for them vpon the croſſe, that they are elect and ſauid, but alſo it dothe make them knowe, that it whiche they ſee, is by diuine inſpiracion, that it is the holye ſpirit whiche teſtifieth vnto theyr ſpirite, that thei are the ſonnes of God.<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> Whoſe teſtimonie
<pb facs="tcp:4370:17"/>
is more clere, open, firme, and certeine, then al the outward oracles and miracles of the world, which without the inward teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the ſpirit, can leaue vs none other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doubtful. Now, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he that hath in him Chriſt and the ſpirit of God, doth fele, know, and perceiue it: it is clere by Chriſt which ſayde that the world knew not the holy goſt, but that he was knowen of them in whom he was. And by ſaynct Iohn, which ſayd alſo In this we know that Chriſt is in vs,<note place="margin">i. Iho. iii.</note> euen by the holy goſt which he hath geuen vs.</p>
               <p>Therfore ſayd Paul, trie your ſelues,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. xiii.</note> make ſome profe of your ſelues, is it poſſible that ye ſhould not knowe Chriſt in you, if ye be not reprobate? And in an other place, know ye not how ye are the temple of God, &amp; that the holy goſt dwelleth in you? The holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite goth ſearching throughout,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii Eſa. xxxii. Roma. xv. Luke. i.</note> and iudgeth euery thing, &amp; fayth is ſo clere, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſheweth vs the profunditie of god: &amp; thou wilt that it be blynde of it ſelfe. Yea Paul ſayth, that the holy goſt is geuen to vs, to the ende we myght know thoſe thinges that haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs of Chriſt.<note place="margin">i. Teſa. i.</note> The kyngdom of God is peace (as writeth Eſai and Paul) withoute ſeruile feare, in much certentie. Therefore as Chryſt ſawe, that he was in the fauoure of his father, and his beloued ſonne, ſo alſo
<pb facs="tcp:4370:18"/>
do the electe ſe them ſelues, all thoughe not with ſo cleare lighte and certentye, but that they goo ſomtyme doubtynge, ſtumbling, and wauering. But they oughte wyth the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles to pray Chriſt to augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their faith.<note place="margin">Luke. xvii.</note> And ſeke with their good workes continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes more perfect their ſaluation and vocation, that therby as by the effectes or fruites they ſhuld come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ful riches of certeine perſwacion, and vnderſtandinge of their election and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">i. Teſſa. i ii. Timo. iiii Rom. viii Gala. ii. ii. Cor. iii.</note> Paule alſo knew he was in the fauour of God, in faith, hope and charitye, elected the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God, ſaufe and ſuer, and that he had the holy gooſte and Chriſt within him, when he ſaid that he was one of them that Chriſt was come to ſaue, and that he knewe in whome he beleued, that he loked for the Crowne, that nothynge colde ſeperate hym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of God, whiche had elected him before the conſtitution of the worlde, that he had the ſpirite of adopcion of the ſonnes of God, and that Chriſte was he, who lyued and ſpake in him. Saint Iohn alſo ſaied: we are ſuer we know God, and that we liue in him, worldlie and carnall beaſtes are they, which know not God in the holye goſt,<note place="margin">Gala. ii. Ioh. xiiii. i. Cor. ii.</note> nor thoſe thynges which be his, euen as men not regenerate, they are ruſtical payſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4370:18"/>
abiecte and baſe a ſpirite, that they can not beleue that God hath loued them ſo much, that by the death of his only begotten and moſt intierly beloued ſonne, he would ſaue them, take them for his chyldren, and make them his heyres: But aſtonied of theyr ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they are euer afrayed of hell. Where the regenerate fele in ſuch ſorte the charitie of God in Chriſt, that they knowe them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be ſaued. Neyther canne they once thynke that Chriſte (who hathe all his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers power and ſhall be theyr iudge) wyll refuſe, loſe, or dampne them, and geue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence agaynſte his brethern and members,<note place="margin">Math. xxviii</note> for whom he dyed on the croſſe, and would dye agayne if it were neceſſarie.<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> They haue in them alſo the holye goſte for an earneſte of theyr ſaluation. But if God had geuen vs nothyng but our beynge, ſhould not we for that onlye benefite, feele ſo muche the greate goodnes of God, that we myght be ſure and certayne of our ſaluacion? And nowe he in euery creature dothe ſparkle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs loue, with innumerable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, yea in Chriſte vpon the Croſſe, caſteth he the flame of perfecte charitye, and ſhall not wee feele ſo muche the goodnes of God that wee ſhould beleue to be his electe?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:19"/>If one onlye ſhulde be ſaued I wold truſte ſuerly to be he, if al the men &amp; angells wold tel me that I were dampned, I cold not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue them, althoughe thei did alledge al the reaſonnes poſſible, but I wolde euer giue, more truſte to Chriſte alone, who vpon the croſſe, with his bloude and deathe, doeth tel me I am ſaued, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wold to al the reſt, for he alone, hath more power in me, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the reaſons &amp; authorities without him. Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uided only y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſe him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liuely fayth, dead for my ſaluacion. Yea in that caſe ſeing my ſelfe,<note place="margin">Gala. i.</note> by Chriſt, to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God, I wold with. Paule exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the very angels as ſuperior to them, if thei wold ſaie the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, or gaineſaie the goſpel, and the great loue and benefit, which in that caſe I ſhuld fele by Chriſt. Paraduenture thou wilt ſay it ſemeth me not, that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſuer of mi ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, becauſe I am fre to do euell, ſo mai I ſinne &amp; be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned. Our life is in ſuch ſort variable, that to giue a certeine iudgement, we muſt tarye the end, for euery one wolde haue thoughte, that Iudas ſhuld haue bene ſaued when he was called of Chriſt, &amp; yet it is ſene, that it is contrarye. I anſwere, thou begileſt thy ſelfe, in thinkinge thy ſaluacion dependeth vpon the likelyhod of thy worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> Paule affirmeth, that God hath elected
<pb facs="tcp:4370:19"/>
vs by his mere mercy in Chriſt, not bicauſe we were holy, or for that he foreſawe oure good workes, but becauſe we ſhould be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſhould do good workes, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryng in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ſhould dye in his fauour and grace: Inwardly doth God cal his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>electe, geueth them knowledge of him,<note place="margin">Roma. viii.</note> and doth iuſtifie &amp; glorifie them. Therfore doth Paul adde and ſay, if God be with vs, who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be againſt vs? And he ment if we be once electe, we can no more loſe our ſelues: mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, there is nothing that can let the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of God. Yea euery thing ſerueth to ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion, euen ſinne. Therfore where thou ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſte, thou mayſt ſinne, it is true, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture thou ſhalt ſinne. Neuertheles if thou be the electe, thou ſhalt algates ryſe againe and be ſaued: wherof thou mayſt be certein and ſure, ſo that once at the leaſt thou haue perceyued thy ſelfe in Chriſt, and by Chriſt ſaued, neither thou oughteſt ſo much to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre in thy ſelfe, as that thou ſhuldeſt not much more truſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of god, know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng that the Goſpel is not the law, but mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, and know thou that when the electe fall in any ſinne (whiche God doth not permitte but for the benefite of them, and the other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte) whileſt they are in that erroure, they fele in them ſelues, a certeine hydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vertue,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:20"/>
whiche withholdeth and refrayneth them, from doyng worſſe, it biteth, nippeth, and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth them of the euel fact, and doth en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce and ſpurre them to conuert. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth euer a certeine hate of ſin, although they be ſometime ouercome of frailtye. So that they neuer turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God with al their power, nor run wholy to vice with a loſe bri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dell. God hath them euer for his owne, and gouerneth them as his lawefull Childrene. And ſpeaking ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their herts he ſaith that which he ſaid to his Apoſtles:<note place="margin">Luke. xii.</note> feare not litle flocke, for it hath pleaſed youre father, to giue you his kingdom of his mere goodnes although you be vnworthy. And if thou wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt bring in Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ſayth, none kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth whether he be worthy of hate or loue, I anſwere. It is clere (chyflie by the wordes whych folow) that he ment, that man were he neuer ſo iuſt &amp; wiſe, was ſo blinde in this world, that he cannot know by the workes of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is by proſperity or aduerſity, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of him ſelf, he be worthi of hate or loue. And this is bicauſe God giueth his giftes ſo indifferently, to the good and euell, to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte and reprobat. Thou wilt ſay yet, Paul ſaid:<note place="margin">i. Cor. xiiii.</note> my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth not reproue me yet am I not therby iuſtified before God, therfore it can not be knowen. But I anſwere, that
<pb facs="tcp:4370:20"/>
thentent of Paul was to ſaye, that thoughe by grace of the Lorde he had miniſtred the Goſpel, in ſuche ſorte, that his conſcience dyd not rebuke him of any erroure (whiche was imputed vnto hym for a ſclaunder of falſe chriſtians) neuertheles he held not him ſelfe iuſte for this, neither was he iuſte, he iudged him ſelfe iuſte by Chriſte, and not by preaching the Goſpel irreprehenſibly in the ſyght of man, but yet not in the preſence of God, for that he hath not preached it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whole force of ſpirit, fayth, &amp; loue. So that here Paul did conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them, which iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues iuſte by theyr owne workes, but he doth not reproue the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thoſe, which iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; ſaued by the bountie of God, &amp; death of his only begotten ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: but doth approue it. With Paule alſo agreeth Iob,<note place="margin">Iob. ix.</note> when he ſayde, that although he were iuſte, he durſte not iudge him ſelfe ſo, that is, he durſte not holde hym for ryghteous, by his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ryghteouſnes and workes, but by the iuſtice of Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Sence then that it maye and oughte to bee knowen of vs, that wee are in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure of God, and hys electe, lette vs force vs continuallye to encreaſe in more knoweledge of the Goodneſſe of God:
<pb facs="tcp:4370:21"/>
ſo that firmely eſtablyſhed in the lyuelye faythe of oure ſaluacion, we maye as chyldren render hym all honoure, laude, and glorye: by Ieſus Chriſt oure Lorde. Amen</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sermon">
               <head>¶Vvhether it be good or euel to beleue that we are electe: the fourthe Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome ſaye that it is euel to beleue that we are electe, bycauſe, that as the beliefe to be reprobate, bringeth men in diſpeyre: ſo the beliefe of eleccion, is cauſe of preſumpcion. But the iuſte and the holy flye bothe the one and the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie. They are not exalted in preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, beleuing to be electe: nor fallen in the botomles pyite of diſpeyre, wyth beliefe of dampnacion, but kepe the meane waye, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtanding betwene both. And I ſay that it is true, that none ought to diſpeyre, or yet to preſume, but aſſuredlye to hope and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue to be ſaued and elected: Mary by oure
<pb facs="tcp:4370:21"/>
owne workes, this is an euyll vyce, and ought to be fled. But to beleue to be elected and ſaued by the liberalitie of God, by the deathe of Chriſte vpon the croſſe, and hys workes: thys is no preſumpcion, but a hope whych hath regard (as diuine &amp; theological vertue) not to oure merites, but onlye to God by Chriſte. And as we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not loue him ſo muche, but that we euer lacke of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ſo can we not to muche hope &amp; truſt in him. Yea we lacke euer bycauſe we do not promiſe of God ſo muche as we ſhulde do, he that beleueth to be ſauid, becommeth not proud, nether magnifieth him ſelfe, nor his worckes, but the goodnes of God, and the grace that we haue by Chriſt. Therfore is it not euell. Peraduenture thou wylt ſaie one oughte to ſtande in feare. I agre therto, in the reuerend and ſonnelike feare, the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che importeth obſeruaunce of reuerence to God, but now not ſo vile:<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> for we ar no more ſeruauntes but ſonnes, not Hebreues but Chriſtians, we are not vnder the lawe but grace, we haue God for our father, and not onlye for a Lorde.<note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> Therefore our office is to loue him like childrene, and not to feare him, as ſeruauntes,<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> ſence that we haue the ſpirite not of ſeruitude but of adoption, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonnes of God. If our ſaluacion did depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:4370:22"/>
in any parte vpon ourſelfes: I wolde ſaye we ought to fear our da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yea to be ſure therof: but ſence it is al in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of God, therfore beholding not oure ſelues,<note place="margin">i. Iho. iiii.</note> but hys goodnes diſcouered in Chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe we may be ſuer and certeine of our ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Perfect charitie chaſeth away al ſeruile feare, &amp; faith neuer douteth if it be perfect: the feare then of our damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> groweth of imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our charitie, faith and hope. We ought neuer to feare the mercyfulnes of God, but our owne wyckednes. Thou woldeſt ſaye, if we were wholie confirmed in grace, we ſhuld not nede to feare, but we ſynne daylie, therfore it is neceſſary to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in doubte. I anſwere that yet thou goeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute, to builde my hope vpon my worckes the whiche ſhuld be no hope but a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. If we ſhulde hope wyth condition if we do well, and perſeuer therin, my hope ſhulde ſtande wyth deſperacion, for of my ſelfe I knowe I ought to deſpaire. If I had the ſynnes of the whole worlde, yet wold I moſte ſtedfaſtly beleue to be ſaued without anye feare of dampnacion, nether may this be ſayde to be euell, for that I woulde not builde my hope but vpon Chriſte. If thou woldeſt ſaie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſeth men to abſtein fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, therfore it is good.
<pb facs="tcp:4370:22"/>
I aunſwere, that it cauſeth men to refrayne in their owne loue, as doth the fear of death wherby they become dayly more ſenſuall in them ſelues, and therfore truely, worſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly. Feare worketh wrathe in God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the lawe doth: and although it cauſe the abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome euill outward worke, neuertheleſſe the venime remaineth within, the which is ſo much the worſe, as it is more vnited to the inwarde partes, yea that feare geuen to the vngodly, is the ſcorge of God. The electe (knowinge that God in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent lyfe doth punyſhe more the legittimate chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then the baſtardes) abſtaine alſo by this feare more then the other. But truly the loue of God, the quicke feelynge of hys greate goodnes, to beleue firmely by Chriſt and his grace to be the ſonnes of God, elect and ſure in deede, are thoſe thinges whiche mortifie vs to the worlde and to ourſelues, and maketh ſynne diſpleaſaunt to vs, euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the botome of the hert. Therfore where the ſeruile feare maketh Ipocrites, the ſon-lyke loue maketh true chriſtians. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſai, to beleue ſo, is a thing veri perilous becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> herof thei take occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue idle, yea to geue them ſelf to al vice, ſaiyng I wil make my paradiſe in this world, for euerye wai I ſhal be ſauid, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alredi I am elect.
<pb facs="tcp:4370:23"/>
I anſwere that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one beleueth to be elect and perceiueth in ſpirite the mercifulnes of God in Chriſte, then God taſted in Chriſte hath in the herte ſuch efficacie and ſtrength, that he can not offende, but is forced to dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe the worlde, &amp; is rapt to ſo highe eſtate that he falleth to obliuion of the world, him ſelfe and his paradiſe, ſetting only God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eies.<note place="margin">Ioh. iii,</note> Therfore ſayeth ſainte Iohn. Who ſo hathe this faithe, ſanctifieth hym ſelf. So as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chariti ſpringeth but good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, euen ſo is it, of this faith &amp; hope. Know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt thou where in is the parille? In beleuing to be elected, by theire workes, and by bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge in Chriſt not ſtedfaſtlye, but to haue only a certaine barraine, idle and a dead o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion therof, the which ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſte life, in ſuche ſorte that of that colde and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frutefull faythe, they may take occaſion to geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Idelnes, and all vyce. But now not of that perfecte faith, the which is effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous in doinge worckes by loue, beinge an enflamed lyghte,<note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> the whiche is neuer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute burninge. If alſo thou wouldeſt ſay in beleuinge to be electe thou ſhouldeſt perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture be begiled, therfore it is euell. I wold yet anſwere, that I wolde ſoner geue faithe to the holy goſt, whiche teſtifieth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hartes of the electe, that thei are the ſonnes
<pb facs="tcp:4370:23"/>
of God (as Paule writeth) then to the that woldeſt put me in doubt of it.<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> The electe to heare inwardlye in their hertes a ſpirituall voyce, quicke and deuine, whiche biddeth them not doubte, and that they are ſuer of theire ſaluacion, &amp; that God loueth them, and hathe taken them for his children, and that thei can not periſhe: the teſtimonie of God is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mans.<note place="margin">Ihon. x.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Therfore not onlie he is to be beleued afore man, but he deſeruethe to haue giuen vnto him vndoubted credite. If thou woldeſt ſai, it might be, not the ſpirite of God but their imaginacions. I ſaye, that what ſo euer it is they knowe better then thou,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii.</note> for that (as Paule ſaithe) none knoweth what is in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but the ſpirite of man, that is within hym. Farder I am ſuer, that the ſame ſpirit whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thc ſaith to me, I am elected is the ſpirite of God bicauſe the faithe I haue of my electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſpringeth not of my worckes, but onlye of the goodnes of god, vnderſtand in Chriſt and for that of his goodnes can growe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gyle nor falſhod, therfore am I ſuer to be in the trueth. Deceites &amp; falſhedes, mai, &amp; do come, of the belefe to be ſaued, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and elected: Moreouer the lyght whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the electe haue of their ſaluacion, is ſo cleare, that they do not onlye ſe them ſelfes
<pb facs="tcp:4370:24"/>
ſuere therof, but they knowe alſo, that the lyghte and knowledge they haue, is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall &amp; diuine. But we ſuppoſe as thou ſayſt, that in beleuinge to be electe onlye by Chriſte and the goodnes of God, I myghte be begiled (whiche is falſe and impoſſible) yet wolde I ſtill ſaye, let me be deceiued for it is good to be ſo begiled, ſence I can finde no thinge, that ſo much doth kindel me into a ſincere and pure loue of God, as to beleue to be elected bi his mere goodnes. Therfore vſinge it to make me inamored of God, I oughte not to be withdrawen, chifelie for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am happye, onlie bi that faythe, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che whoſoeuer is voide, is not yet entred in to the kingdome of God, where is nothinge but ryghtuouſnes peace and Ioie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. iiii.</note>Finalli Paule beleued to be elected as in many places he ſaythe, yea he gloried ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (neuertheleſſe in God) and ſo to beleue he induced others, the which, if it had bene euel, he wolde not haue done. Therfore if it be not euel, let vs alſo with Paule, glori vs by God in Chriſte, who likewyſe induced the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Luke. x. Math. xv. Math. xvi.</note> to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr names were write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heauen, that theyr heauenli reward was ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuous, &amp; that they ſhulde iudge the xii. tribes, &amp; therby brought them to beleue thei were electe, and that is alſo ſuer, that if
<pb facs="tcp:4370:24"/>
that belefe had bene euell, he wold not haue cauſed it. Thou wilt ſaie, thou oughteſt not to compare thy ſelfe, equall wyth the ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. I ſaie it is true that I oughte not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to be like them, or holy by myne owne worckes, for while I preſume of my ſelfe, I muſte of force become a deuell, but it is not euell to compare with the ſaintes in veritie, for they were humble, and in beleuing that they were elect, they gaue to God all laude and glorye bicauſe they did not beleue to be of the electe for their merites, but for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. And wold to God, I mighte beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> firmelye and with ſtedfaſt fayth, the ſacred ſcriptures are ful, that we ought not to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peire of our ſaluacion, but that we ought to hope and beleue to be all readye ſaued, and dayly to certifie oureſelues therof bi doing good worckes,<note place="margin">ii. Pet. i. i. Iohn. iiii.</note> which are a teſtimonie to vs of oure election, and that we ſhulde alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in charitye, to take from vs all feare of oure dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the end we may ſerue God without feare, in rightuouſnes and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lineſſe as zacharie ſayde.<note place="margin">Luke. i.</note> And likewiſe wee ought to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perſeuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the good w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faith to obtein it. Therfore to truſt to be ſaued, &amp; of the elected &amp; to hope &amp; beleue to be ſaued &amp; of the electe, is not euel. Paul al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaithe: oure hope was neuer confounded nor dyd ſhame to them that had it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:25"/>And lykewyſe that fayth, was neuer begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Wherfore then is it euyll that I beleue ſtedfaſtly to be ſaued by Chriſt? Let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde then wyth open eyes of liuely fayth, Chriſte vpon the croſſe, in whome we ſe preſentlye the goodnes of God in the face in ſuche ſorte, as we maye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng pilgrimes, to thende wee may render to him al laud, honor &amp; glory through Ieſus Chriſte oure Lorde. Amen</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="sermon">
               <head>¶ Vvhether it be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye to ſaluacion to beleue that we are elected or not: the fyft Sermon</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. xi. Mar. xvi Iohn. iii.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ayth is very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye, becauſe that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute it, not onlye God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not bee pleaſed, but he that beleueth not ſhall be condempned, and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready iudged. But it is alſo impoſſible, that one that doth not beleue to be elected ſhould beleue as he ought to do any of the articles
<pb facs="tcp:4370:25"/>
nceeſſarie to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And to proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is true, if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> beleueſt not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou art one of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, thou beleueſt not in God, in the maner that thou arte bounde, bicauſe that it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to haue a certeine dead opinion that Godi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but thou muſte effectuouſly beleue that he is thy God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he loueth the, that he is propiciatory to the, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to the, that he hath moſt ſpecial cure of the &amp; cauſeth euery thinge to ſerue the to ſaluacion, &amp; therfore that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte electe. Yea who ſo beleueth not that he is electe, doeth not fele in ſpirite, the benefite of Chriſte. Therfore beinge without Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ephe. i. Gala. iiii.</note> he is with oute God, and knoweth him not as Paule wryteth. Then howe is it poſſible that thou mayſte beleue perfectli that he is thy father if thou do not beleue that thou arte his ſon, and therfore his heire &amp; ſaued.<note place="margin">Gala. iiii.</note> Thou canſt alſo neuer earneſtlie beleue that God is om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nipotente, if thou vnderſtande not, that con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually he vſeth his omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie towards the, in doinge the good. Whiche when with the ſpirite thou dideſt proue, thou ſhuldeſt of force beleue thy ſelfe to bee his heyre, if thou beleue not thou arte elect, howe cauſte thou beleue that God hathe created the heauens, and thearthe, &amp; that he ſuſteineth &amp; gouerneth all to thy behofe hauing of the
<pb facs="tcp:4370:26"/>
moſte ſinguler cure: it is nedefull, that with liuely ſayth, imbraſinge al the world for thy owne, thou perceiue effectuallye the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, in euerye creature. And when that is, thou ſhalt be inforced to beleue, that thou arte the ſonne of God. Thou canſte not alſo beleue in Ieſu, that is that he is to the Ieſus and ſauioure, if thou beleue not that thou arte ſaued, nether canſte thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that he is thy Chriſte, that is to ſaye a Prophete kinge and prieſte, if thou fele not in ſpirite, that he doth illuminate and ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the, as a prophet, rule the as a king, and as an onlye prieſte is offered for the vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. The which if thou dideſt beleue thou ſhuldeſt alſo beleue to be elected. How ſhalt thou beleue that Ieſus is the only begotten ſonne of God, thi Lord come into the world to ſaue the, and geuen to the, with al his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine treaſures and graces, if thou doſt not beleue, thy ſelfe to be one of his lambes, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> cauſte not beleue (as thou arte bounde to do) that he died for the, nor perceiue his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue charitie, ſo that with Paule y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maiſt ſaye,<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> nothing can ſeperate me from the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of God. It is neceſſarye to beleue, that Chriſt vpon the croſſe hath ſatiſfied for thy ſinnes, and that he hath reconciled the, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied to his father and ſaued the, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:4370:26"/>
that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God: he that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth (as he ought) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt is ryſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to iuſtifie vs, doth alſo know him ſelfe ſaued, &amp; ſo he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perfectly doth vnderſtand that Chriſte our head is aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; entred for vs in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of paradiſe,<note place="margin">Philli. iii.</note> perceiueth him ſelf ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen with Chriſt, &amp; alredy bi hope being aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> practiſeth with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> minde in Paradiſe, where Chriſt is ſitting in peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thinges celeſtial: he ſaieth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul, we are made ſafe by hope,<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> it ſuffiſeth not to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhal iudge the quicke &amp; the dead y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which alſo the deuils beleue, but that the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence ſhalbe al in thi fauour, hauing to thi iudge, him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> died vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe for thee. We ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not liuely beleue the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſte, if we fele it not in oure ſelues: and if we do feale it, we ſhalbe forced with Paule to ſaye, the ſpirite of God rendrethe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to oure ſpirite that we are the ſonnes of God, therfore heires and ſaued.<note place="margin">Roma. viii.</note> Neyther is it inoughe that there is a church of God, but thou muſte beleue to be a porcion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp; one of the lyuely ſtones, &amp; therfore one of the electe. And to beleue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of ſainctes, thou muſt feele, that as a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Chriſt, he doth perticipate his grace w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou art therby ſaued, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not only that
<pb facs="tcp:4370:27"/>
he dothe pardon ſinnes, but that he hathe pardoned the thine, and ſo elected the. Euen ſo thou muſt beleue, that thou ſhalt riſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and haue life euerlaſting. Then ther is no article of our faith, that can be beleued in ſuche ſorte as it ought to be, of thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che do not beleue they are elected. To the Chriſtian it is then neceſſary to beleue that God is his God, and father: that he worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all for his benefite, and that Chryſte is come, was borne, hath liued, died and riſen againe for his ſaluacion, ſo that with liuely faith he imbraceth Chriſt wholi for his own with al his treaſur and grace. And likewiſe al his life, death, reſurrection, aſſention and glorye, and perceiueth the charitie of God in Chriſte, as if there hadde bene no mo but onlye him ſelfe in the world, and that Chriſt for him onlye, wold haue wrought and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, no les then he hath done. The which when thou doſt beleue, thou ſhalt perceyue thou arte elect. Yea he that beleueth not he is electe, can not praye as he oughte, beinge withoute faithe, withoute the whiche (after Paul) we can not effecteouſly recommende vs to god,<note place="margin">Roma. x. Iaco. i.</note> bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt aſke in faith, if we wil aſke in veriti &amp; be hard, now if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not to be his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; heire, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> (as Chriſt taughte) ſay our father, &amp; as a ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:4370:27"/>
with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence aſke him grace. Praier may wel be made, of infidels and Ipocrites, but lyke foliſhe ſcoffers and mockers. When y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaieſt, halowed be thy name, thy kingdome come, thou muſt haue in the, the ſpirit of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option of the ſonne of God. And as the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is moued of vehemente loue, pure and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, to deſire the kingdome and glory of the father: ſo muſt thou (ſeinge the, the ſonne of God) with a deuine ſpirite, by the force of loue, aſke and deſyre that thy heauenlie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be honored, and reigne in his elect with oute rebellion. Likewyſe ſhalte thou neuer thancke God with all thy herte, if thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not to be one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect: yea if thou ſhalt doubte therin, or thinke to be dampned in thy harte, and in thy lyfe, and paraduenture alſo with thy wordes, thou wilte diſpraiſe him, that he hath giuen the a beinge, that he hath create the world, ſente Chryſte, and ſo the reſt his benefites, and wilt ſaie. If I am not ſaued, what do theſe thinges profit me? it had ben better for me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had neuer ben,<note place="margin">Mar. xiiii</note> as Chriſt ſaid of Iudas. If I ſhalbe damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the death of Chriſt ſerueth me not, but doth inflame &amp; burne, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites: y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt not in perfection the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke god, if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> feare dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> But who ſo bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth he is one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect &amp; therby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al things
<pb facs="tcp:4370:28"/>
ſerue him to ſaluacion, euen the verye trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, he holdeth for a ſpeciall grace and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, in them perceiuinge the goodnes of God, he giueth him thanckes with all his herte. Who ſhal he be that committeth him ſelfe holy to the gouernaunce of God (as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one oughte to do) if he beleue not that God is his father, that he pardoneth him, &amp; doth take of him moſt ſinguler cure? Other wiſe they ſhal neuer truſt in God, but with Adam ſhall feare him, and flye, ſekinge to hide him ſelfe from the face of God, nether is it poſſible, to loue God in veritie, honor him as he ought to be honored and approue for iuſte and hollye all his worckes, and ſo delite wholye in him, if he fele not in Chriſte ſo much the goodnes of God,<note place="margin">Gala. iiii.</note> that he ſe him ſelfe hys ſonne &amp; alſo heire. If he know not him ſelfe to be a ſonne, he ſhal feare as aſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt and in all his worckes haue reſpecte to him ſelfe, his paines, diſpleaſures, incom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modites, diſhonoures, and hel, or els to this paradice, and not to the glorye of God. As he that ſeeth him ſelfe a ſonne, lord of al and heire and ſuer therof: ſuch a one worketh on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by ſtrength of ſpiirt, &amp; veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of loue to the glory of God, to whome he hath tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his whole intent, &amp; to that ende ordreth his whole lyfe. Alſo it can not be poſſible, to
<pb facs="tcp:4370:28"/>
loue thy neighbour as thi ſelfe, as a brother in Chriſt, and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame bodie, if thou do not beleue to be in the nomber of the ſonnes of God. And finalli ther can not one good worcke be done, but of them that are regenerate, ſonnes of God, members of Chriſte, and haue in them the holy ſpirite which teſtifieth in their hertes, that they be the ſonnes of God. And mai parteli be ſene howe falſe and vngodlye, is the doctrine of the antechriſtians, that where as it is cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye neceſſarie to beleue that we are elected, &amp; alſo aboue all thinges moſt commodious thei force the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to withdraw euery one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this fayth, perſwading them to ſtand in doubte, as thoughe they had wherin to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſte the goodnes of God,<note place="margin">Oſee xiii.</note> vpon whome onlie dependeth oure ſaluation, as our da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion doth of our ſelues, But let vs praye to God to open our eyes, to the ende they maye no longer blaſpheme, but render to God all honor, laude, and glorie, by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſte our Lorde. ☞ Amen. ☜</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:4370:29"/>
               <head>¶ If it be good to ſeeke to know wherfore God hath ſome electe and ſome reprobate: the ſyxt Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy deſyre maye be wycked, as it is in many, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it apeareth that it ſhould haue ben better, if God (who being of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as he is) had elected all men, and ſemeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that in this God hath lacked of charitie, yea in theyr language, they ſay in their herrte ſecretly. If we had bene God, we would haue elected all, and would haue had more charitie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he. Now behold, whether this be vngodly, folyſhe, proude blaſphemy, or not. They Imagine to haue more loue to the ſoules, then he, that for to ſaue them gaue his onely begotten and dearly beloued ſonne vpon the croſſe.<note place="margin">i. Iohn. iiii.</note> There are ſome other, to whom it ſemeth on the one ſyde, that god can not erre: and on the other parti, hearinge that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued many, they thinke the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. They are not certeine by fayth, that God can not erre, and that al that he willeth, muſt nedes be iuſte. Therfore to make it clere, they go
<pb facs="tcp:4370:29"/>
ſearchyng, wherfore he hath not elected all men, and they would fynd a cauſe where is none. If ſuch were godly, they ſhuld quiete and ſatiſfie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, &amp; ſhuld haue their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie in the deuine pleſure, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſearching to aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any hler. It is euyl the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſeke wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore god hath elected ſome, &amp; other ſome not if this grow of the ſuſpicion that God may, or haue erred. The godly knoweth certeinly by faith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he can not erre, &amp; hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſteth. There are ſome that aſke after it of arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcion. They woulde be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that god had elected them for theyr good workes, to haue wherein they myght glory of them ſelues. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they hearſay that God hath elected them by grace, it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth them, they gainſaie it, ſeming them there reſteth nothinge to glory in. And they perceiue not that thys is the whole glory of the humble and true chriſtiane, to be ſaued by the mere grace of God, and Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied, and to glorie only in God by Chriſte, and in them ſelues not to ſe, but thynges worthy to be aſhamed of, to thend y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to God only be honour and glory.<note place="margin">i. Timo. iiii</note> It groweth alſo to many of vnreuerence, for if they coulde ſe howe inacceſſible the maieſtie of God is, howe irreprehenſible is his wyll, and howe inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible is his wiſedome, they wold
<pb facs="tcp:4370:30"/>
not ſet them ſelues to diſpute with God, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially if they knewe howe blynd,<note place="margin">Roma. ix.</note> darke, fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticke and folyſhe they be. And who art thou ſayd Paul, that wilt diſpute with God, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and contend with God? Paul was re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turned from the thyrd heauen, where he had heard ſecrets, ſo hygh that it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſpeake to man. Neuertheleſſe doynge reuerence to the diuine ſecret iudgementes he ſayd: O profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d riches of the wiſedome and ſcience of God, how inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible are his iudgementes? And man, blynd, folyſhe, and vngodly, is ſo high minded, that he wil do wronge to God, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pning him, and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proue his holy, iuſt, &amp; irreprehenſible iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. And how many are thei that ſeke to knowe, ſpeake &amp; wryte of it, and be comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therfore? And al that they ran Imagine by force of their owne wytte, and naturall knowledge (which can not perce ſo hygh ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes) they put in writyng. And they are as arrogant, as if they were in goodnes and ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pience ſuperior to God: to be adored of the worlde, they condemne the workes of God. Ther are mani which are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to know aſmuch as God hath vouchſaued to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs, but they wold knowe alſo a great deale more. But it is not the office of a good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, to wyl to know al the ſecretes of his Lorde: yea the ſonne ought to contente hym
<pb facs="tcp:4370:30"/>
with the ſecretes of his father, and to know of it only, as much as is reueled to him and to be ſuer and certeine, that he wil not faile, to manifeſt al that ſhal be expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for him, euen ſo we ought to contente vs, to knowe that which God hath, and dothe reuele vs, knowing that he doth loue vs in ſuch ſorte, that we haue not wherin to doubte, that he wyll fayle to manifeſt vnto vs, all thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes, the knowledge wherof ſhalbe profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and neceſſari.<note place="margin">Ihon. xv.</note> Yea chriſt him ſelfe ſaid that he had made knowne, all that he hadde heard of the father, oure office is to ſeke, to taſte and fele with the ſpirite, that which he hath opened to vs, and we may alſo deſire to know all that pleaſeth God to reuele vs, for the benefite of oure ſoule, and his glory, nowe for that God (to beate downe carnall man, to the ende that to him, be geuen al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, laude and glorye) hath voucheſafed, to open in the holy ſcriptures, wherfore he hath elected ſome, &amp; other ſome he hath not: Therfore we mai &amp; ought to ſeke to know it that we may ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more honour God: but we ought to beleue it to be ſo, as God hath declared, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent vs with that way, God hath taken, in electing &amp; reprobating, neither to thinke nor ſuſpect, that God hath erred, nor ought to deſyre any other waye,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:31"/>
but to be ſatiſfied and pleaſed, with ſo much as pleaſeth the Lorde, without beinge curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in wyllynge to knowe more, then that which pleaſeth God to reuele vnto vs, and all that to thende that by Ieſus Chriſte we may render him al ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor, laude, &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="sermon">
               <head>¶ Of the diuerſe effectes that it worketh in man to beleue that one eleccion is al in the handes of God, and that of him only it depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth: the ſeuenth Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſeene by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that of one ſelfe cauſe, doth growe ſome times contrary effectes. And is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bi the ſun, whiche hardeneth mire, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etteth waxe: and this is by theyr di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe diſpoſicions. Euen ſo of the belief that our eleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is wholy in the handes of God, dothe ſpringe in men contrary effectes, by theyr contrary diſpoſicions. The vngodlye
<pb facs="tcp:4370:31"/>
perceiuing that in the deuine minde is reſol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued theire beinge, to be ſaued or dampned, they are wroth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, thei blaſpheme him with their hearte, they cal him parciall and vniuſte, they giue them ſelues to do euell I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe, ſayinge euerye waye: that ſhalbe which God hath infalliblye foreſene, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutabli determined, yea their faltes thei caſt in the face of god, thinking y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is the cauſe therof, many alſo deſpaire of their ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; preſume more of them ſelues, then they hope in God, they beleue that they ſhuld be ſaued, if theyr ſaluacion dyd depende vpon them ſelues, &amp; therfore if thei could diſturbe the deuine counſayles, and make that their ſaluacion ſhuld not be in the handes of god, they wolde do it. And this is for that they knowe not their owne greate myſery howe blynd, infirme, frail, and vnprofitable, thei are to God impote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of them ſelues to good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and full of all wickednes, and that thei dyd neuer worke (if it were put in the bala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of deuine iuſtice) that merited not to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and ſo likewiſe they fele not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great goodnes of God, nor the benefits of Chriſt but thincke him to be Irefull, reuengable, diſdaineful, proude, parpetuall, vniuſt and malignaunt, as them ſelfes are. There are ſome whiche haue not perfecte fayth, but
<pb facs="tcp:4370:32"/>
they are not ſo vngodly as the fyrſte. Nowe theſe when they heare ſay, or thincke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſaluacion is all in the handes of God, they remaine confuſed and euell contented. And this is alſo for wante of knowledge of the goodnes of God, they truſte partly in God and partly in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, they loue not God, nor truſte nor hope perfectly in him they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine doubtfull, and knowe not whether it be beſt to depend all vpon God or not, and it ſemeth them that it ſhulde haue bene beſte that in ſome parte it ſhuld depend vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them ſelues: &amp; yet thei thincke it wel beinge al in the handes of God, troubled in ſuche ſorte, that thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not tel which to chuſe: Therfore they liue in a great perplexiti. They conſult ſome times with the holye ſcripture or with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue, the knowledge of the truth, &amp; they find that it is al in the handes of God, &amp; they iudge (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their eies are ſomewhat opened to the goodnes of God &amp; their own miſeries) that it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth wel, and that ſo it is beſte, but then harkeninge to humane pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the whiche not beinge wholye mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, wolde haue parte of the glorye to it ſelfe (ſo proude it is.) And as that, that is blynd, and ſeeth not the impotencie and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lignitie of man, it perſwadeth him that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might in ſom part be ſaued bi him ſelf, wher
<pb facs="tcp:4370:32"/>
elles he mai deſpaire, if it ſtand al in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of God. Therfore it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludeth, that it were better if it dyd depend vpon vs, and chieflye for that men become negligent, in thinkinge that it depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth wholi vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God: where thei wold ſtyrre them ſelues to be ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if they dyd beleue that in any parte it reſted in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And although ſuch finde the contrary in the ſacred ſcriptures, neuertheles they force the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the obſcure lighte of their blynde pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to draw it out of the texte, expounding it as may beſte ſerue to their purpoſe. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly perceiue on the one ſide, in ſuch ſorte their owne proper ignorancie, frailtie, impo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tencie, &amp; malice: And on the other partie the great bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of god in Chriſt crucified, that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenteth them to be ſo, all in the hande of God, not only for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath ſo pleaſed god, but alſo for their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie: becauſe that whereas if in the leaſte iote it depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon them, they ſhould holde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Now they fele ſo muche the excellencie of god, that certified of their ſaluacion, thei knowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues elected, &amp; hold it to be ſure ſeyng by faith that it is al in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of one their ſo mightie, ſapient, excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; louing fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. Wherfore by this benefite, thei are ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to loue him ſingulerly, to tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke, lande, and ſerue hym as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his mere glory
<pb facs="tcp:4370:33"/>
wythout reſpecte at all to them ſelues, their hel or heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if God would ſet in their handes, although he would be bounde that they ſhould be able to do al thinges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eaſe toward theyr ſaluacion, yet they wold not accept the bargaine: and that is becauſe thei knowe that they are contrary enemies and traytours to them ſelues: ſo that if they had paradiſe in theyr handes, then they ſhould ſet it fal to the ground. And alſo for that, thei do make experiment and proue ſo great cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie of God in Chriſt, that it certifieth them of theyr eleccion. They can not thinke that Chriſte beyng theyr iudge, and diyng vpon the croſſe for them, ſhould geue ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them: yea they know, that who ſo be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leueth in hym ſhall not be iudged,<note place="margin">Ioh. iii.</note> but ſhall be ſo certeine of his ſaluacion, that he ſhall not nede to make diſcuſſion of his lyfe, for there ſhal not be any to accuſe hym, neither ſhould it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that thoſe which haue the ſpirit of God, and are his ſonnes, the brethern and members of Chriſt, ſhould be examined and iudged.<note place="margin">Roma. viii.</note> But with Chriſt thei ſhal be iudges of the other. Therfore the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, ſure of their ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wold not chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Chriſt theyr iudge wyth any in thys world, although it were theyr deare frynde or nere parent.<note place="margin">Math. xix</note> Yea if God did put in theyr arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:4370:33"/>
to haue Chriſte for theire iudge or els to be their owne iudges of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, with full power to geue ſentence in their fauour althoughe it were not iuſte, yet to be appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, they wold for all this, chuſe Chriſte to be theyre iudge, for that they truſte more in him then in them ſelues. Alſo thei loue God ſo much, that they wold not glory, but only in him by Chriſte. And this is al there true glorye. Yea if they colde let or diſturbe the deuine counſayle, or if it were neceſſarye to be dampned they wold chuſe, rather to be in paine for the will of God, then in all the pleaſures, diſagreinge to the deuine wyl (if it were poſſible) they counte them ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy to ſuffer for the wyll of God. They holde them ſelues happye to honoure him with ſufferinge, and wyth beinge where it pleaſeth to their lord, they lamente onlye of the iniuries they haue done to God, but of that whiche God wyll do of them with the ſpirite, they are contente, although the fleſh be repugnaunte and wold not ſuffer. This ſhuld be a hel to them, when God (if it were poſſible) wold not diſpoſe them to his glori but to vſe them to his honoure they wolde ſatiſfy them ſelues with all, and content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know it ſo to be the deuine pleaſure: now theſe are in a continuall paradiſe by faithe
<pb facs="tcp:4370:34"/>
allreadye they haue had the ſentence geuen in their fauour, by hope they are aſcended into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſayinge with Paul: we are made ſafe by hope,<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> and by loue they enioye God. In the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then of the belief, that their electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is all in the handes of God, groweth firme fayth, and hope to be ſaued, the loue of God ſincere and pure, and chryſtiane vertues, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the frutes of good worckes. I wolde haue pitie on the firſte ſorte, but their deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> groweth of an vngodlye minde, yea it is moſte impietie, to deſpayre of the goodnes of God, moſte perfect, ſhewed in Chryſte crucified, as in one his liueli Image. I haue compaſſion of the ſecond, and enuye at the thirde. The ſeconde maye eaſelye be cured with ſhewinge them theire frailtie, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauncie, and malice, and on the other partie the omnipotencie, infinite ſapience, perfecte goodnes, pitie, mercy and chariti of God, ſhewed in Chriſte vpon the croſſe. Of the firſte, I do not deſpaire vtterli, but I know well it is verie difficile to cure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Math iii</note> but God is of power, of the ſtones to rayſe vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they haue nede to be praied for, and that the Lorde take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before their eies, ſuche veiles of ignorauncye, &amp; make them ſee their owne great miſeries, and the incomprehenſible goodnes of God, to the
<pb facs="tcp:4370:34"/>
ende that reknowledging al their wealth to come of God, they maye render him al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, laude, and glorie, by Ieſu Chriſte oure Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="sermon">
               <head>Howe it ought to be an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lamente that God hath created them foreſeyng theyr dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the eight Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are manye, the which althoughe of God thei haue had their being, &amp; manye other benefites, neuertheleſſe they thanke him not, but are vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. They are ſorye, and lament of all the wealth they haue had of him, ſaying: Lord, if the being where thou haſt geuen vs, with the reſt of thigyftes, dyd ſerue vs to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ſhuld tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke the therfore: But bicauſe they ſerue vs not, but to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacion, therfore we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine vs of the. Nowe to theſe ought to be anſwered thus: Either you beleue to be of the electe or not. If they ſaye yea: it ought to be ſayd to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye ſhuld tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke God of ſo much grace, that he hath ſhewed to you already, in choſinge you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo baſe a being, to ſo high an eſtate, &amp; you lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t your ſelues: behold if your ingratitude be greate.
<pb facs="tcp:4370:35"/>
And if they wolde ſaye we are not ſorye for oure ſelues, for we beleue to be elect, but for compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on thoſe poore ones y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reprobate. Then I wold to be ſayed, it is no true pitie to haue compaſſion vpon them, that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlye, againſte the deuine goodnes, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cheifly in Chriſte crucified. Thincke you happelye, to haue more charitye then God? take heede that youre demaunde, wherfore God hath create the reprobate, grow not of the doubte, that God can do them ani iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. Do ye feare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, being verye righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes,<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> yea charitie it ſelfe, can do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ani wrong? But if you liueli and verilie did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue to be electe by Chriſte, by mere grace &amp; mercye of God, ye ſhulde feale in ſuche ſort the deuine goodnes, that there cold not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into youre minde ſo vngodlie conceytes. They are in good cuſtodie, beinge in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of God. They are in the power of one which neuer did, nor mai do, one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſte cruelties, yea he neuer doth iuſtice, but it is with great mercie. Will ye knowe more of the deuine ſecretes then Paule? which rapt to the thirde heauen,<note place="margin">i Cor. i.</note> heard thinges ſo highe and ſo ſecrete, that to man it is not lawfull to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of?<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> It ſuffiſed him onlie to know Chriſt crucified. Is it not thincke ye inough to you to knowe Chriſt crucified, in whom
<pb facs="tcp:4370:35"/>
are hidden all the treaſures of the wiſdome and ſcience of God? And if that ſuffice you, in Chriſte is ſene non but the electe, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reprobate are withoute Chriſte, &amp; in Chriſte only ought we to contemplate and beholde our election, your office ſhuld be to attende to your ſelues, to encreaſe dailye bi Chriſte, in greater knowledge of the bounti of God,<note place="margin">i. Timo. iiii.</note> and to make certeine to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world with good worckes, youre vocation and election, and not to be ſo curiouſſe of other, forgettinge your ſelues. And if thei wold ſaie,<note place="margin">ii. Pet. i.</note> we doubt and feare alſo leaſte we be reprobate, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we complaine vs, and wold know whi he hath created vs, forſeing our dampnaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: nowe theſe muſte be exhorted not to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, but to contemplate &amp; loke in Chriſte, in whome they ſhall ſe them ſelues elected. And ſo thei ſhal not haue wherof to take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to lament, after it muſt be ſayd to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for as muche as ye do not beleue verelyet be of the electe, it is a ſigne, that ye haue not liuely lyghte of Chriſt, nor of his greate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, &amp; not knowinge Chriſte, it behoueth to ſaye with Paule that ye know not God in veritie, and that ye are without him.<note place="margin">Gala. iiii. Ephe. ii.</note> And howe is it poſſible the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that you beyng with out God, and without the true knowledge of him, ſhulde vnderſtande and knowe his
<pb facs="tcp:4370:36"/>
high ſecretes? It is not poſſible to know ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the deuine iudgements then God. Ye be therfore without faith, and I proue that it is true, becauſe that if ye had faith, ye ſhuld ſe ſo clerelye that God doth euerithing wel and can not erre, that you wold aſke non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon. And for that who ſo is without faith, is franticke concerninge the deuine thinges, it muſt nedes be ſaide that you are euen ſo, and now is it a franſi, your demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding a reaſon of the creacion of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, neither ſhulde it be poſſible to ſatiſfie you, till ſuche time your reaſon were healed bi faithe. Yea while that ye are ſo withoute lighte ſupernaturall, beinge therof not able to conceiue, he that ſhuld ſerch to quiet you with reſones, ſhulde alſo enter into a franſi with you. Humble then your ſelues to God and aſke him faith and not reſones, becauſe that thinges ſupernaturall, can not be ſene but by faith. Inſatiable is the golfe of foliſh and frantike curioſiti, the godlye adore the high &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God and with humilitie, thei are contente to taſt in them bi faithe, ſome drop, of the deuine ſapience &amp; goodnes: where the vngodly pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuming without faieth, haue a wil to perce, to the inacceſſible counſaile of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in darckenes, become madde and folyſhe: ye perceiue not that ye want y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true
<pb facs="tcp:4370:36"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuyng of God. If ye thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God may erre, or do any thing vniuſtly: you wyl per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes adde light to that perfect light, rule the diuine ſapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, correct that infinite good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, iudge that iudgeles iuſtice, &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne that ſupreme mercy &amp; charitie. If thou didſt ſe the hyghnes &amp; magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, &amp; on the other ſyde, the baſenes &amp; vanitie of man, and how in al thinges he depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ye ſhuld ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he neuer puniſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuche ſorte, that they deſerue not to haue a greater punyſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, being ſo franticke &amp; proud, ye are not capeable nor worthy to haue lyghte of the hygh iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, yea you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to remayne ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed. And for that, it is the iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, that for the ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt peine of your hel, ye ſhuld go euer with your troubleſome thoughtes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſinge by ſuch darke &amp; inextricable maſes. Therfore although I could geue you a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al the workes of God, I wold not do it. Humble you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God, &amp; aſke him fayth, for with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only ladder, we aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſecretes of God. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhall haue faith, ſeinge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clere &amp; ſupernatural light, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god doth all thinges well, ye ſhall no more care for a further reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if alſo y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſeke it, it ſhuld be with a godly mynd to be ſo muche the more able the better to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde God, in his iuſt &amp; holy iudgementes.
<pb facs="tcp:4370:37"/>
And then I wold ſaie to you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God might haue ſaued al, but he hath not willed it, yea forſeing the dampnacion of the vngodly, he created them,<note place="margin">Proue. xix.</note> not for to ſaue them, or to the end thei ſhuld be ſaued, but to ſerue him ſelf of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more to be ſhewed brighte and gloryous,<note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> to the world. The which is a more beutyful, more riche, more happy, and more wonderfull ordinaunce, then if ſynne had neuer be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. And this is bicauſe Chriſte and his electe (of ſynne) haue taken occaſion, to honoure God more then if the world had euerben innocent, and God with greateſte ſapience, dyd reduce all the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres, into a more meruelous order, then if the world had neuer ben diſordred by ſinne. If ſinne had not bene, the ſaintes had neuer bene perſecuted, inpriſoned, and ſlayne, no more Chriſte crucified. Where then ſhulde haue bene their victorye, their Palme, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes and crownes? And if the reprobate wold ſay: we are forced to confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath done well to permit the ſinnes of the electe, that after as the prodigall ſonne, of his errour &amp; miſeries, toke occaſion to open his eies &amp; know him ſelf, yea, &amp; to returne to his father, to humble him ſelfe to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with hart, &amp; axe him pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and therbi to taſte the fatherly charitie, when he pardoned him, in
<pb facs="tcp:4370:37"/>
more perfecte maner, then he had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: ſo the electe, of theire ſinnes take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the better to know them ſelues, and the bountie of God, and it is no ſmall benefite of God, that he ſuffer him ſelfe to be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of his childern, and beare with it, to the end that ſome daye, opening theire eies, thei may ſe their greate ingratitude, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue loue that he beareth them. God alſo of theſe, may be afterwarde ſuerlye ſerued, at euerye noble and great enterpryſe, as of them that are altogether his, not only for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath created and preſerued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but much more becauſe that by ſinne being loſte, with the bloud of his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne, he hath recouered them. And ſo was Chriſte ſerued of Paul, &amp; of his other mighti cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pions, we muſte of force confeſſe alſo, that God doeth well to permitte the ſinnes of the reprobate to excerciſe the elect in vertues, for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter triumphe of Chryſte and his glorie. But it ſemeth that it ſhulde haue bene better, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after that God had ſerued his tourne with them, he ſhoulde touche theire herte, and geue them his knowledge, and his grace, ſo that they alſo of theire ſinnes ſhould take occaſion, to reknowledge theire vice, and the goodnes of God, ſo that they might be ſaued, to them ye ought to ſay: ſence ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:38"/>
that God hath done well, to permitte the ſinnes of the reprobate, ye can not deny, but that for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei deſerue to be dampned. Ye are alſo forced to ſai, that god dampneth them iuſtli, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence that thei haue ſinned: God then doth wel to permitte them to ſinne, and when they haue ſinned, he may iuſtli damne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe that voluntarilie thei did ſinne, and the falte was theires and not Goddes. Ye can not then complaine you of God, if he dampne you, but are conſtrained to ſaie he doeth well. And if they ſaie it is true, but yet it ſhulde ſeine vs to be better, and with his greater glorye, if after he were ſerued of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he wold ſaue them. To theſe I anſwere firſte that is beſte, whiche pleaſeth God, &amp; becauſe it pleaſeth him to dampne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that is beſte. Then if God in the end of the life, ſhuld geue light to all, And ſo at laſt euery one ſhuld conuerte, thei wold do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie more enormious ſinnes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do. For the vngodlye wolde ſaye, we maye do eueri euell, let vs take oure pleaſure and liue fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, without any feare, for euery waye in the end we ſhalbe ſaued. And for that one onlye ſinne is worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the peines of the damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, therfore it is beſte, that they be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Theire dampnation ſerueth alſo to the electe, in as much as that ſeruaunte whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4370:38"/>
when he ſeeth iuſtice done to his felowe ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaunte that before woulde haue ſtrangled hym, knoweth the goodnes of his Lorde, and the malignitie of the man: ſo the electe, by ſeyng in the dampned the iuſtice of god, do come to more knowledge of his mercye and iuſtice, and alſo of theyr owne miſerie. God is ſerued then of the reprobate, to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreate and ſetforth his glory, and vſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for inſtrumentes, not only whyle they are in this lyfe, but in death and in hell. His glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie alſo is more diſcouered (as Paul wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) by hauinge in his great houſe veſſels of golde, of ſyluer, of wodde, and earth, of mercy, &amp; of wrath. But let vs thanke God that he hath elected vs, and praye hym that he geue vs ſo muche lyght of his goodnes, and ſo muche feruencie, that althoughe he wold euer be angry wyth vs, not onely we ſhould be content, but that we holde it for a ſinguler priuiledge, that he wyl vouch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſafe in ſuch maner to ſerue him ſelf of vs, to thende that in euery ſtate, &amp; for euer, we may render him al laude, honour, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, by Ieſu Chriſte oure Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:4370:39"/>
               <head>¶ Wherfore God hathe elected vs: the nynthe Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſhuld be no leſſe then a very folyſhenes, when one entendinge to ſpeake of colores, ſhuld brynge in the opinion of one that is borne blynd, and not illuminate by miracle. So is it mad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe in the thinge ſupernaturall, to alledge the iudgement of them that are not inſpired but with naturall vnderſtandinge. And by aduenture haue talked, of high, hydde &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſecretes, euen as it hath ſemed well, in their owne blind and darcke vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, hauinge therby their eies euer open, to mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifie man. Now bicauſe that of the ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural matters, ther is ſo much knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as is reueled and opened to vs. Therfore lokinge in the holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> I find that God hath elected vs by Chryſte, that is, that God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge in the progeny of Adam, ſaw nothing there that was worthy of our election: but tourninge the regarde to his own goodnes and Chriſtes, in whom he was ſo wel plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">Math. iii. Ephe. i.</note> that bi him he did electe vs, he therfore choſe vs not becauſe we were holie, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:4370:39"/>
we ſhulde be, ſo that the deuine grace founde no ſaintes but made ſaintes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did Paule geue thanckes to God, that had made vs mete to the enheritaunce of ſaintes. He choſe vs then becauſe it pleaſed him ſo, for he loued vs frelie without ſeinge in vs any thinge, worthy therof.<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> He elected vs (as wryteth Paule) after the decreed pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe of his owne will, to the laud and glory of his fre mercie and not for our worckes. So that not bicauſe we were iuſte and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi in his ſighte, he did electe and cal vs, but (as Paule ſaieth) bicauſe he hath elected,<note place="margin">Roma. viii.</note> therfore he doeth call, iuſtifie and glorifie vs. In ſuche ſorte, that he willed not the end for the beginninge ſake, but the beginninge for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end ſake. He hath ſaued vs, after Paul not by the worckes that we haue done, but by his mercy. In a nother place he ſaieth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath deliuered and called vs with his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye vocarion not after oure worckes but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his pourpoſed mercie,<note place="margin">ii. Timo. i</note> giuen all readie to vs before the creacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world: ſo then, as of the ſecretes reueled to the litel ones and hidden from the wiſe and prudent Chriſte did giue none other cauſe, but for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo it pleaſed the father,<note place="margin">Math. xi.</note> ſo of our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there may no nother cauſe be alleged, but only be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe it is the pleaſure of God. Paule wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:4370:40"/>
that the purpoſe that God hath made vs, maye not depende vpon our workes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhulde not be firme as it is, nor we ſure, as Chriſt ſayth we are, and Paul alſo. If thou woldeſt ſay, that Paul to the Rom. ſpake of the eleccion of Iacob &amp; Eſau,<note place="margin">Roma. ix. Iohn. x. Rom. viii. Roma. ix.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fyrſt byrth, &amp; not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge the heauenly inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I wold anſwere that Paule with that trope, dothe declare the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of the eternal eleccion to paradiſe, other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe the eleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iacob, ſhuld be in vaine, in the which is ſene (touching the thinges of the preſent life) nothing but calamitie &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. But the principall intente of Paul is to proue that although the carnall Hebrues be not ſaued, it reſteth not therfore, that Ieſus is not the Meſſias, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the promiſes were made to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual hebrues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which in faith do imitate &amp; folow Abraham, &amp; they are the elect.<note place="margin">Mala. i.</note> When God alſo in Mala. ſheweth to the Iues that he hath loued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe he loued Iacob of whom they deſcended, and hated Eſau: His reaſon had ben vnuailable if God dyd loue and thoſe by workes. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes might haue anſwered: if thou dideſt loue Iacob &amp; the Hebrues, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou dideſt forſee their good workes: and in lyke caſe thou wouldeſt haue done to Eſau and the Gentils,<note place="margin">Roma. ix.</note> if thou haddeſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſene
<pb facs="tcp:4370:40"/>
any good workes in them. But Paule ſheweth that the Meſſias is come alſo to the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tils, becauſe God geueth his gyftes with out hauinge reſpecte to workes. If thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund wherfore he hath elected the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Paul anſwereth, becauſe it is written: I wyl ſhew mercy on whom it pleaſeth me.<note place="margin">Roma. ix.</note> Therfore Paule doth inferre and bringe in, that para<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſe is not his that wyl, nor that runneth or laboreth by hymſelfe to get it: but his that God wyl ſhewe mercy vnto. He myght alſo haue anſwered, that although God hated Eſau, before he was borne, &amp; before he dyd ſinne, he is not therfore wycked, for he had hym not in hate or he did foreſe his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But he ſaith that he doth indurate who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wyl, to ſet forth the brightnes of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And to his purpoſe he doth alledge the example of Pharao. Now tel me howe it is poſſible that God can forſe in vs any good, if he determine not to geue it vs? Thou wilt ſay, he ſaw that ſome could vſe well frewil, and ſome not, therfore he choſe the fyrſt, and refuſed the ſeconde, they coulde not vſe it well, wythout hys grace.</p>
               <p>Wherefore then dyd he determine to geue that grace of well vſynge to the one and not to the other?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:41"/>It behoueth to returne to the deuine wyll, and ſaie, becauſe it pleaſed him not: for the vſinge wel of fre wil is the effecte and frute and not the cauſe of election. Peraduenture thou wylte ſaye, he did determine to geue grace to all, but he ſawe that ſome wold vſe it wel and thoſe he choſe, and ſome euel, and thoſe he forſoke. But tell me, the vſe of that grace is alſo the gyfte of God, wherfore did he not determine to geue that grace to all, &amp; alſo to vſe it? Thou muſte nedes ſaie at laſte alſo, becauſe it pleaſed him not. If thou wilt ſaie, thoſe that vſed it not well, was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thei lacked the grace to vſe it, no more then the other, but they did not occupye it when they had it, the deſalte was theires &amp; not of God, nor of the grace. If it were ſo, we ſhuld haue wherin to glorye in our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. But Paul is in the contrarie, &amp; willeth that to God ought to be rendred all honour and glorye,<note place="margin">i. Cor. iiii. Romm. iiii. i. Timo. i. Iero. i.</note> ſo as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him commeth al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. We might alſo of our ſelues, ſeperate vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reprobate, and ſo our hope ſhuld not be al wholy in God, our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not be certeine and ſuer, as Chryſt ſaid: nor the cauſe of oure election ſo hid,<note place="margin">Ihon. x. Rom. iiii.vi.ix. and .xi.</note> as Paule ſaieth it is, yea fre mercie ſhulde be no more fre merci, if we might be ſaued by worckes and paradiſe ſhuld be a rewarde, and not a
<pb facs="tcp:4370:41"/>
gyfte cleane agaynſt Paule. The Hebrues dyd mo warckes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gentils, and neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles he did choſe the gentils, and reproued the Iewes, that ſoughte to be iuſtified by theyr workes. God from the beginning for ſawe in vs nothing but repugnancie and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt his grace, being by the ſinne of Adam, the children of ire, proue,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii. Gene. viii. Rom. xi. Pſal. xvii.ii. Reg. xxii. Pſalm. xliii. i Cor ii. Iaco. i. Ihon. xv.</note> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to all euyl. Paule calleth our eleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the eleccion of fre mercye. Dauid ſayth: he ſaued me, becauſe he loued me, and becauſe it pleaſed him. He ſaueth then his electe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he delitethe in them, and diſtributeth his mercy, after his owne wyl. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath begotten vs voluntarily by mere mercye, and not by our workes: ſo that the .xij. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels dyd not choſe Chriſte, but he choſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Apoſtleſhip. So we be not they that haue choſen God to ſaue vs, but God is he that hathe choſen vs to ſaluacion. Euen as Paul was called withoute workes by free mercy, becauſe it pleaſed God: ſo he was elected to ſhewe his mercie,<note place="margin">Acte. ix. Gala. i. i. Timo. i. Ephe. ii.</note> and the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunt ryches of his glorie. It is humilitie it ſelfe, to beleue that we are choſen by grace. Thys opinion geueth al glory to God, and to vs only confuſion. And becauſe we can not erre in glorifiyng to much the fre mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and bountie of God, and abatinge the
<pb facs="tcp:4370:42"/>
pryde of man. Therfore it is moſt ſure, yea, although it ſtode not wyth the holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as it doth. And the more it diſpleaſeth the carnal man, becauſe it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>foundeth al hys glorye, ſo much the more it is pleaſing to the ſpiritual, becauſe it magnifieth God, Chriſt, his fre mercy, &amp; the goſpel. And to ſay my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, it pleaſeth me beſt, to be all wholy in the hande of God. Yea if mine eleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were in my cuſtodie, I wolde (if I myght) render it vnto God, in whoſe hand, it muſt of force be better, and more ſure. Yea woe to vs if in the leaſt point it did depend vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues. Se then what becommeth of them that ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gine (although falſely) that it dependith on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the goodly workes that they do, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues elected again, wher on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partie, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt ſe, that thoſe which with lyuely faith, beleue to be by the mere mercy of God, and by the death of Chriſte, in the number of the electe, and ſonnes of God (for that they fele in Chriſte, and by Chriſt, the greate charitie of God,) are by ſtrength of the ſpirite and loue, forced to do worckes to bee wondered at: not ſeruile, for they ſee them ſelues heyres, but the worckes of a ſonne, ſincere and pure to the glorie of their lyuely father, beynge preuented by loue.</p>
               <p>If thou wouldeſte beleue, we are not
<pb facs="tcp:4370:42"/>
worthye to be ſo elected by free mercye, I woulde aunſwere, neyther that Chryſte ſhoulde ſuffer for vs vpon the Croſſe, but dyd he not therfore die? Chriſte hathe not elected vs, becauſe we were worthy therof, but for the glorie of his goodnes:<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> The cauſe of oure eleccion is not then to bee ſoughte, but at the diuine wyll.</p>
               <p>Of the reprobate, I entende not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, wherefore God hath caſt them of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is neyther nedefull to vs, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to knowe. It ſerueth to humble vs, and to knowe better the greate goodneſſe of God, that wee are elected by his grace, and not by our workes.</p>
               <p>The chriſtiane ought to beleue to be one of the choſen,<note place="margin">Ephe. i. i. Cor. ii.v.</note> and it ought to ſuffiſe hym to haue Chriſte for his booke, in the which he ſeeth hym ſelfe electe, and to knowe that that apperteineth to hym. And althoughe Paule to the Romanes ſpake a worde ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it was but incidently or by the way, for it doth apeare it was not his principal inſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſeke the cauſe wherfore God dothe repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate and caſte them of. It is inoughe for vs to thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the omnipotencie of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng infinite, hath neither limites nor bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:43"/>
therfore may he do with his creatures with out contradiccion: and the deuine wyl may do of them, determine and wyll al that, that with hys whole power he maye do, beynge the whole ruler, and neceſſarily moſt ryght in all hys wyll, yea the very ryghteouſnes it ſelfe. Wherfore honoringe the bryght and lyghte iudgementes of God, let vs beleue that God dothe not condempne, but wyth iuſt and irreprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible counſayle, albe it the iuſtice of his iudgementes be to vs incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible,<note place="margin">Romm. xi.</note> and that none is in hell, but by hys owne wyckednes: Our office is then to humble vs, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent vs in the diuine wil, reknowledgyng that we be not worthy, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe we fuffer all puniſhment, to ſet forth the brightnes of the glori of god, to whom, for al his workes, is due all honoure, laude and glorye by Ieſus Chriſte oure Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:4370:43"/>
               <head>Whether the electe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be damned or not: the .x. Sermon</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Barn. iii. i. Ioh. iii. ii. Teſſa. ii.</note> god ſeeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginninge and for euer al thynges, and hath of all, certeyne and infallible ſcience, &amp; particularlye knoweth hys electe, theyr lyfe and their end. So then as God, by the neceſſitie of his beinge can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be corrupted, neither diminiſhe nor aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beyng infinite and wythout ende, nor be altered, beyng moſt ſimple and pure, nor chaunge place, beynge vnmeaſurable, fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng al places: ſo alſo maye not his determi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacions be chaunged: neither by ignoraunce for lacke of foreſight and conſideracion,<note place="margin">Roma. ix.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for defaulte of power, ſince he can not be letted or weakened, nor his wyl reſiſted. Neyther may he chaunge by malyce, or for want of ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful goodnes, for his purpoſes are moſte good and fyrme.<note place="margin">Mala. iii.</note> God then is immutable in all his doynges, chaungeth not as chyldren, nor lyke olde men, but as Dauid ſaith: The counſayl of the Lord ſhal ſtande for euer: that muſt nedes be that god hath determined, neither is it in our power to chaunge his purpoſe, diſturbe the diuine
<pb facs="tcp:4370:44"/>
counſayles, deſtroye diuine ordinaunces, nor lette hys wyll, whych is Empreſſe, and owres of the hand mayden. Therfore what God wylleth, muſte bee, and not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he muſt wyl after our phantaſie. Nowe becauſe we are not to be elected,<note place="margin">Ephe. i.</note> but (as Paul wryteth) God hath elected vs, before the conſtituci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the worlde, and is in his determinaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons immutable, it is of force therefore to be as he hath determined. So likewyſe he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and knoweth all thynges frome the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng, wyth certeine &amp; infallible know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: it is therefore neceſſitie that, that bee, whyche he hath foreſeene, or elles it muſte nedes be that God may chaunge, and that of oure lyfe and ende he hathe no perfecte knoweledge, but a doubtful opinion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo he may be beguiled, and that ſaying were a moſt wyckednes. Thou wylte ſaye to me, thou arte deceyued in imaginynge that aboue is tyme, and ſucceſſion of tyme, and that God hathe foreſeene and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all that is yet to be, ſo that hys determi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacion and knoweledge is already paſſed, in ſuche ſorte, that he can not otherwayes knowe, nor wyl, without his chaunge whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is impoſſible. And therfore thou iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſte it neceſſitie, that all that come to paſſe, whiche he hathe foreſeene and determined.
<pb facs="tcp:4370:44"/>
But it is not ſo, for aboue there is no ende or ſucceſſion of tyme, nyght nor daye, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was nor ſhall be, as there is here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneth the heauens, ther is onlie all the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſente tyme, and onlye one moſte clere daye of one inſeperable inſtaunte, the whyche by hys eternitie extendeth to the ſucceſſion and proceſſe of all tyme. And I anſwere, that I knowe ryght well, that to God euery thing is preſente, although beyng vnder thys ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Sphere, where is folowynge of time to make vs better vnderſtand, we vſe with Paule to ſaye he hathe elected vs: but tell me, doeſt thou beleue that the eleccion of thoſe that are in thys preſente lyfe, and lyke wyſe thoſe that ſhall be, is nowe in beynge in effecte and preſent before God, or not.</p>
               <p>If thou ſayeſt no, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal it neuer be, for w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him is no time to come. If thou ſai yea, then maye it not be wythoute mutacion in God, ſence thou graunteſte it once to be.</p>
               <p>If thou wouldeſt ſaye it myght be no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge, yet it coulde not be not beynge, but in the inſtaunt of the Godhead, in whych thou graunteſte all thynges to bee, for as muche as aboue is no ſucceſſion or courſe of tyme, and ſo in that ſelfe inſtaunt indiuiſible, thou woldeſt haue it poſſible, not to be any being and yet a beyng: for aſmuch as it is not ſo.
<pb facs="tcp:4370:45"/>
Therfore if thou conſent that God (I ſaye not hath ſene) but doth ſe and determine all thynges, ſence that God is immutable, and his ſcience infallible, &amp; that ther is no courſe of tyme, by all meanes, lykewyſe it is to bee ſayde, that, that muſt nedes be, which God wyth perfect infallible knowledge doth for ſee, and ſtedfaſtly determine. Becauſe that (if wyth God there were any time paſt) eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as that coulde not, not be whiche God had foreſene by his infallible preſcience, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutably determined: no more can that thing not be, which he doth preſently ſe and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Thou wylte ſay, I graunt that al that ſhal be, which God doth foreſe and ordeine, and ſo God ſhall not be beguiled, nor yet chaunge, but yet neuertheles it myghte be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, although it ſhal neuer be. But thou ſeeſt not howe thou art deceiued, thou grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt that al the electe ſhal be ſaued, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou ſayeſt they may be dampned: And wherto ſerueth this, may be, if in effect they ſhall not be dampned. Therfore this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but in wordes, it is curiouſe and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. Nowe, as if thou woldeſt graunte that an elect could be damned, thou ſhuldeſt be forced to ſaye that God maye chaunge. Therfore thou ſayeſt, that all may be ſaued, which argueth yet that the electe may be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:45"/>
and ſo thou muſte nedes confeſſe, that God may alſo be beguiled, &amp; vari in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce, which is impoſſible. That the elect then may be dampned, it is a thynge falſe, hereticall, and vnpoſſible: it can not be vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by no ſentence compound nor deriued, ſence that in God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no mutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Therfore if he be elect, he muſt nedes be ſaued, and it muſt nedes be ſayd, that the eleccion of them that ſhall be ſaued (I wyll not ſay hath ben but ſtandyng in that eterni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie) is in beynge becauſe that if it were not nowe, it ſhulde not be hereafter, ſence there neither is, nor can be with God, but alway the preſent tyme. Then God hauinge in his diuine mynde geuen vs paradiſe frome the beginninge, and when he geueth neuer repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth (as Paule writeth) it is of neceſſitie to ſaye that the electe be ſaued.<note place="margin">Rom. xi.</note> Paule writeth that the eleccion of God is firme, and the di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uine purpoſes ſtedfaſte, and that the Lorde knoweth his wyth perfect infallible knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">Roma. iiii Roma. ix.</note> which ought to be to vs a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion, whereupon we maye ſtablyſhe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted fayth of our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Paule ſayd, that thoſe that God hathe knowen for his, and therfore elected &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſaue them, thoſe he hathe predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to be conformable to the Image of his
<pb facs="tcp:4370:46"/>
ſonne, and thoſe, hauynge them after crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he doth call wyth an inwarde callynge, in ſuche ſorte, that they anſwere agayne, for becauſe they are the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of God, therfore they heare hys voyce, and beleue by beynge ordeyned to eternall lyfe. Yea he draweth them, and geueth them a newe herte, and theſe that he calleth he iuſtifieth, he geueth them Chriſte, and the lyghte of him, faythe, hope, and charitie, and all other chriſtiane vertues apparelynge them, he dothe enrich them wyth many gyftes, treaſures, and gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, &amp; afterward doth happely glorifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therefore from the fyrſte to the laſte it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that the electe muſt nedes be ſaued. Paule added and ſayd: if God be wyth vs, who can be agaynſte vs: meanyng, if God hath elected vs, and determined to ſaue vs, he beynge omnipotente, and hath taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hym thys enterpriſe to ſaue vs, who ſhal let hym? Yea he would haue ſayde, no man, becauſe that Chriſte ſayde,<note place="margin">Iohn. x.</note> none can take them out of the handes of my father: it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth not to God as to man, whyche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye tymes dothe wyll a thynge, ſeketh and canne not fynde,<note place="margin">Rome. xi.</note> as the Hebrewes, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſought theyr ſaluacion, and coulde not atchieue it, and that becauſe they ſoughte it not by Chriſte, by fre mercy, nor by faythe,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:46"/>
but by workes. It is not ſo wyth God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he, when he wylleth any thynge, it commeth to paſſe, and his eleccion (as wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth Paule) commeth to effecte. Moreouer God hath geuen his electe to Chryſte,<note place="margin">Iho. x.xi. &amp; .xvii</note> and draweth them to hym, and thoſe that go to hym drawen of the father, he chaſeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, as hym ſelfe ſayde: he loſeth them not, but knoweth them for hys ſhepe, he cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth them to hym, they heare hys voyce, he prayeth for them moſte effectuouſly, and is euer hearde. For them he ſhed hys bloude,<note place="margin">Math. xv.</note> and gaue his lyfe, euen as for them onely he was ſente, and came into the world, to them he dothe manifeſte God, geueth them lyfe, and maketh them happy. They are then in good handes, beynge in Chriſtes, out of the whyche none ſhall take them, as hym ſelfe hath ſayde.<note place="margin">Iho. xi. &amp;. xvii.</note> They may peryſhe that are the ſonnes of perdicion, as Iudas, but not the chyldren of eleccion. The elect are ſure, for ther was neuer none of them that peryſhed nor neuer ſhal, yea it is vnpoſſible,<note place="margin">Math. xiii</note> for chriſt ſpeakyng of the falſe prophets which ſhuld be in the kyngdome of Antichriſt, ſayde they ſhoulde ſeduce the verye electe, if it were poſſible, for to ſhewe that it was not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yea for theyre ſakes, thoſe dayes ſhall be ſhortened.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:47"/>Al that God hath wrought and ſhall worke is for his electe, for whome he dyd create the world, &amp; preſerue the ſame, ſente Chriſte into the worlde, and wylled that for them he ſhulde dye vpon the croſſe, for them he hath moſt ſpeciall care. If God made ſuche accompt of the Hebrues, that to thend their name ſhoulde not be forgotten on the earth,<note place="margin">Deute. xv.</note> he dyd ordeine, that if the fyrſte brother died wythout chylde, the ſecond was bounde to rayſe vp ſede to his brother: thinkeſt thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil not make rekening of his elect whoſe names are written in heauen? Yea, I wyll thou know,<note place="margin">Luke. x.</note> that although Chriſte be he, by whoſe meanes al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect are ſaued, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe not by his impotencie, beyng geuen to hym all power, but becauſe the thynge of it ſelfe is impoſſible.<note place="margin">Mar. x. Math. xxviii.</note> Chriſt can not ſaue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, nor damne an electe. Nowe muche leſſe is it in our power, if we be electe, to dampne our ſelues, or if we be reprobate to ſaue our ſelues, yet ought we not to ceaſe to worke wel, becauſe that if we are ſure to be dampned, we are yet bound euery way, for his infinite goodnes, moſte hyghly to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hym. Let vs then geue thankes to god that hath not only by mere mercy elected vs for hys, but to thende we myght be ſure of oure ſaluacion, hath ordeined that oure
<pb facs="tcp:4370:47"/>
dampnacion ſhal not lye in our owne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (beynge his electe) and with thys geueth vs ſuche grace, that we may in this preſent lyfe, render hym all laude, honour, and glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, by Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="sermon">
               <head>Whether God do agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, harden and blynd the hertes of men or not, and in what maner: the eleuenth Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is read in the holye ſcriptures,<note place="margin">ii Reg. xvi. iii. Reg. xxix ii. Reg. xxiiii Exo. i.vii x.xi. and .xiiii. Eſa. lxiii. Ihon. xii. ii. Cor. iiii. Roma. ix. &amp; .xi. Gala. iii.</note> that God put in Saula wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpirite to vexe hym and a liyng ſpirite in the mouth of the Prophets to beguyl Achab, &amp; that by Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he moued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hert of Dauid to nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the people againſt his precept. And moreouer he doth harden, blynde, and make groſſe the hertes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and geueth them ouer in to a peruerſe mynd. And Paul wryteth, that he hath ſhut vp al men in vnbelief &amp; ſinne. And although many helde for vngodlines thys maner of ſpeaking, &amp; therfore thei do not onli abſtain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cinge ſuch lyke wordes, but alſo go about to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better, eme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge
<pb facs="tcp:4370:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:48"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:49"/>
them, forcinge them ſelues to brynge them after their pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſie, to ſuche a way, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue a kynde of godlines therin. And I thinke they are moued to do this, to thende that of theſe thinges men ſhould not take occaſion to thynke that God were the cauſe of ſynne, or els to imagine wyth the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be .ii. firſt beginnings, the one good, cauſe of the good, the other euel, cauſe of the euell. Neuertheles I wyll not, ought not, may not wyll to be more holye then God, that ſpeaketh in holye ſcriptures. And it is more wickednes to wyl to correct the longe of the holy goſt, becauſe that none ſpeaketh nor can ſpeake more circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpectlye then he, nor with greater thyrſt of our ſaluacion, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the zeale and honour of God. Wyth al this euery one ought to knowe that we are the cauſe of ſynne and not God: yea it can not be thought, that God is a God, if it be not thought that he is wythout faulte, wythout euell, infinitely good and iuſt. Therfore as to vs is due all confuſion, ignominie, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, reproche and euel, ſo to God all honor, laude, and glorye. It is not euel then to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce theſe wordes, in the maner that they are wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaiyng that God doth agrauate, harden, and blynde, but it is good.</p>
               <p>Thou wylte ſaye, tell me how theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:4370:49"/>
are to be vnderſtande, that God dothe harden, blynde, and ſuche lyke: ſo that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may not take any occaſion of offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. I aunſwere, that after the opinion of ſome, God doth harden, and ſo blynde the herte of a perſon, in as muche as he foreſeeth and forepreacheth his hardenes, as he did foreſe and foreſaye the obſtinacie of Pharao. But knowe thou, that when he ſayde to Moſes, I wyll harden the hert of Pharao, he wold not onelie ſay, I foreſee that he wyll be hard herted, and I tell it the before, for then the wordes whiche he he ſpake after, ſhoulde not haue agreed therwith, whyche were: for to ſhewe my power, that my name maye be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared throwghout the whole worlde.</p>
               <p>But wyth thoſe wordes he threatened to punyſhe hym, as it is read, that he puniſhed mo people for theyr ſinnes,<note place="margin">Deut ii. Eſai. vi Ihon. xii. Pſalm. lxxx. Roma. i.</note> wyth blynding them, hardenynge them, with lettyng them do after theyr deſyres of theyr owne hertes, geuinge them ouer into a frowarde mynde, in paſſions and ſhamefull effectes.</p>
               <p>Therefore there are ſome whyche ſaye, that God manye tymes dothe harden and blynde ſinners, when ſufferyng, yea geuing them proſperitie, and diſtributinge his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and benefites, when they oughte to open
<pb facs="tcp:4370:50"/>
theyr eyes to ſo greate benignities of hym, and be inuited therby to repent and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge theyr lyfe, they, of this bountie of God take occaſion to become worſe, euery daye more blynde and indurate. But I ſaye that the vertue and alſo the vice ſtandeth not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie nor yet in aduerſitie, but in the men them ſelues. So that as to the electe euerye thing worketh to ſaluacion,<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> and by the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all grace that they haue of God ſerue hym in aduerſitie as in proſperitie: ſo to the repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate, euery thyng ſerueth contrarye, &amp; hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, yet by theyr defaltes as not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie &amp; aduerſitie, but alſo the preachinge of the Goſpel, and the miracles do hurt and hynder them. Therfore Paule ſayd, that as to the electe, Chriſt was the odour of lyfe, ſo to the reprobat,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. ii.</note> he was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> odour of death. It is nedeful then to ſay that God doth har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den and blynde the hertes of the reprobate, not becauſe he geueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduerſitie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, nor becauſe he ſuffereth them, and ſheweth them many benefites, but for that he geueth them not grace to vſe them, and the commoditie therof, to the glory of God: It may be truly ſaide that he dothe harden and blynde the hertes of the ſinners, when he taketh from them, or geueth them not his grace, nor the vnderſtandynge of his wyll,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:50"/>
wyl, becauſe that in ſuch caſe, it is force that man remayne blynd and indurate, and that euery thynge ſerue them, to the diſhonor of god, wher as if they had that inward grace euen of theyr ſynnes, they ſhould take occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion to honour hym. God doth blynd men, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withdrawyng his lyght, he hydeth his face, and as Moſes was vailed, ſo ſpredeth he the vaile of ignoraunce ouer the herte of the reprobate:<note place="margin">Deute. xxxi.</note> ſo that god in withdrawinge the lyght of his grace,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. iii.</note> blindeth the hertes of infidels, in ſuch ſorte, that not only the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is hyd from them (as Paul writeth) and they erre, but ſtandyng in that darckenes, they can not beleue.<note place="margin">ii. Teſſa. ii. Ihon. xii.</note> And ſo alſo doth he har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den, not for that he geueth proſperitie or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie (of the which the electe alſo are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers) nor becauſe he withdraweth not the grace, but the ſwetenes and the ſenſuall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng therof, of the which many ſaintes wer voyde: nor yet for that he moueth their her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to euell, or cauſe in them any obſtinacie or euell qualitie:<note place="margin">Ezechi. xi.</note> but only in wythdrawyng hys grace, which molifieth a herte of ſtone and maketh it fleſhe, it is of neceſſitie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the hert remain hardened. And ſo lykewyſe he chaſeth awai the ſinner, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth not cal hym, &amp; draw him to him before. Yet for all this god ſinneth not, for he is not holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to geue vs this grace, he may harde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4370:51"/>
molifie after his owne pleaſure, yea the ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner meriteth not onlye to be puniſhed with payne and priuacion of paradiſe, but alſo wyth priuacion of his grace: and that this is true, iudge, if God had kylled Pharao, when he cauſed all the Hebrues chyldren to be caſte into the floude: woldeſt thou haue ſayd that god had bene vniuſte? Surely no. And yet if then he had died, he had ben dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, and remained obſtinat for euer. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore myght not god execute iuſtlye, the ſame ſentence, as concerning blyndyng and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening, vpon others, wyth wythdrawinge hys grace? And on the other partie (as they are preſerued) that ſhal be not amiſſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue him in life for a few mo daies to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued of hym, as of an inſtrument of wrathe, prepared frome the beginninge, to exerciſe his people in vertue, to thende that deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng them ſo diuinely, they myght knowe the great goodnes,<note place="margin">Roma. ix.</note> power, &amp; iuſtice of god. And ſo beynge his name celebrate through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world, he might be feared &amp; loued. And finally all to hys owne glory, as wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Paul &amp; Moſes.<note place="margin">Exo. xxiiii. Pſalm. lxxi.</note> The iudgementes that we geue vpon the ſecretes of god, are verie madnes, if by faith we do not enter into his ſanctuary.<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> God dothe inwardlye call the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte, as Paul wryteth, and they beleue that god, as theyr only father, wyl neuer forſake
<pb facs="tcp:4370:51"/>
them, but ſhall endue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth ſuche grace, that al thynges ſhal ſerue them to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euen ſynne, in the which god wyll neuer let them fall, but for theyr benefite. They are not offended to heare ſaye, that god, by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayning his grace from the vngodly,<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> doth blynd, and harden theyr hertes, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by faythe, to be in the number of the electe, and knowyng that god ſaueth not but by mercye, and damneth not but iuſtlie, ſo much the more are they moued to lyue in pure feare, to humble them ſelues, &amp; render thankes to god, to whom be euer all lande, honour, and glorie, through Ieſu Chriſt our Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="sermon">
               <head>¶ Howe God dothe diſpoſe his grace: the twelfe Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Her are many whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thinke that god to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually doth offer his grace, and that it is in the power of man to accepte it or not, as thoughe they had it in a boudget, &amp; were in their arbitreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; take at their owne wil. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of this their dead, falſe, &amp; erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinion, groweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they liue moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedly, thinking &amp; ſaiyng, god neuer fayleth with his grace, and it is at our choyſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it at our wyll.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4370:52"/>Therfore we may take leiſure &amp; lyne a vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life after our owne way, for we ſhal be ſaued alwaies, a moment of time is enough for vs to repent &amp; be ſaued, ſence it is in our power. Therfore for to flye ſuch an euell, I haue iudged it good to ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not ſo. It is no doute y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath created the world for his electe, ſo that if god had forſene that none ſhould haue bene ſaued, he would not haue created it. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo he dyd preſerue it,<note place="margin">Hebre. i. i Cor. i. Rom. viii</note> to them he hath geuen the Aungels for ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pers, and of them as a father he hath moſte ſinguler care &amp; prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. God wyl not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted aboue their power, yea eueri thyng worketh &amp; ſerueth well to their ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Prou. xxiiii.</note> Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times in a day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt ſhal fal, &amp; ryſe againe, becauſe God is with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and helpeth them in ſuch ſorte, that the more thei are in great perils &amp; neceſſitie, ſo muche the more is god beneficial to them. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god gaue the lawe to the world, ſent Moſes and the Prophetes, them he calleth inwardly in ſuche maner, that they heare his voice, and anſwere him of them he molifieth the herte, and draweth them to Chriſt, as the adama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doth Iron: If they erre, he dothe correcte and chaſten them as chyldren, as it is read of Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſal. xxxi. Ihon. x. Ihon. ix.</note> to them he doth not impute their ſinne, he doth quicken and glorify them, and finally al that god hath wrought, and ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4370:52"/>
worke for hym ſelfe, is for the electe, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſent Chriſt, and when he came, for them he toke vpon hym theyr ſinnes, only for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he prayed, for them he wepte, preached, and dyd miracles, for them he ſhed his bloude, dyed, roſe, aſcended in to heauen, ſent the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye goſte, and ſhal come to iudge the quicke and the dead: yea all that he hath ſuffered, wrought and ſhall worcke, is for the electe, whom he loueth in ſo exceſſiue maner, that he doth attribute to him ſelfe al that is done to them.<note place="margin">Ihon. x.</note> God then beyng gratified with the electe in Chriſt, doth geue vnto them his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, the lyuely lyghte of hym, faythe, hope, with all the reſte of vertues &amp; graces eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial &amp; neceſſary to ſaluacion. And moreouer he geueth them grace to vſe in the honor of god, and be ſerued in his glorye, of all the gyftes and graces which maye be comune both to the good, &amp; to the euel, to be vſed wel &amp; euel, as riches, honour, dignitie, healthe, long lyfe, chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, frindes, ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the giftes of the tonge, to do miracles and ſuche lyke. Of them in parte, Paule made mencion, wryting to the Corinthes.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xii.</note> And alſo geueth them grace to vſe in his glorie, pouertie, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominie, infamie, infirmitie, with all aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitie, and the priuacion of lyke gyftes, euen to the death, god geueth them ſuche grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with euery wind, they ſaile to the porte, and
<pb facs="tcp:4370:53"/>
they knowe that they are no leſſe bounde to thanke god when they are without ſuch gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and in all aduerſitie, then when they haue ſuche thinges wyth the proſperitie of the world, ſence that bithe grace which god geueth them, all thinges worke to good.</p>
               <p>Therfore they are euer contented to bee in the ſtate which pleaſeth the Lorde, neither wolde they chaunge it, if they myght (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the wyll of god) and onlye for that they fele the diuine goodnes, no leſſe in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie then in the worldly proſperitie. In thend when they are fallen to any ſinne, god ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth theyr eies, &amp; maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe, not only the euell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue done, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ſo permitted it for their benefite, to thend they maye the better know theyr owne miſeries and the bountie of god. But ſpeaking of the reprobate, I ſaye, that it is enough for vs to knowe that god is not bonde, nor neceſſited to geue them his grace for theyr good worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: becauſe that the grace findeth not good worckes, but doth make them to be done.</p>
               <p>God neither hath, nor may haue any bonde wyth his creatures. The bondes are all oures wyth god, and ſo muche the more, as that we beyng all loſte in Adam, he myghte iuſtly, not only abandon vs, but damne and punyſhe vs. He is not alſo compelled of
<pb facs="tcp:4370:53"/>
hys perfecte goodnes, mercie and charitie, to not haue created the worlde, he myghte nowe brynge it to nothinge, and diſpoſe all creatures after his owne waye, beinge ſtyl moſte perfectlye iuſte, as he is nowe, and was from without beginning, before he did create the worlde. God maye geue of his grace as much as it pleaſeth him,<note place="margin">Math. xx.</note> when &amp; to whome he thinketh good, yea, and not to geue it without beyng vniuſt, or doinge any minrie. God alſo hath ben of power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doyng any vnrighteouſnes, to create the reprobate, foreſeynge theyr damnacion, to ſerue his owne turne, and to vſe them for in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrumentes, or exerciſe the elect in vertue, to the ende that their victories and triumphes, and likewiſe Chriſtes, myght be the more glorious, and finally all for his owne grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter glorye.</p>
               <p>And moreouer I ſaye, that Chriſte hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth hym ſelfe and his grace manye times frome perſons,<note place="margin">Iho. vii. Proue. i.</note> ſo that althoughe they ſeeke hym, crie after hym, and recommend them ſelues to hym, they fynde him not, nor he heareth them not, notwythſtandynge thoſe ſuch as are not moued to ſeke him, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit them ſelues to him, by the ſpirite, nor for the zeale of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honoure of God, but for their proper intereſt, yea and mani times he doth
<pb facs="tcp:4370:54"/>
blinde and indurate the people, and all is moſt iuſtlie done. And although it be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God hath cure of all, calleth all, wolde ſaue al, died for al, doth illuminate al, dothe raine and power his grace vpon all, &amp; lyke ſentences: I ſaye, it is to be vnderſtand, that he hath cure of al ingeneral, but of the elect in ſpecial, and ſo he calleth al, with a vocaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vniuerſall, but the elect with an inward and ſinguler. When Paule ſaide alſo, that he wold ſaue all, he vnderſtode that, to be of euerie ſorte of perſones. His death alſo was ſufficient to ſaue all, but it is not effectuons but to the elect, and ſo where it is written, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth illuminate and geue grace to al, it is vnderſtand of the elect, of thoſe that are illu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minate.<note place="margin">Math. xiii. Ephe. ii. ii. Teſſa. ii</note> Therfore ſaide Chriſte to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels, to you it is geuen to knowe the miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the kingdome of heauen, Paule ſaid likewiſe, that the ſaith which is the gifte of God, is not al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. It is well true alſo, that God doth illuminate al, in aſmuch as there is no perſon that hath not had ſome lighte &amp; knowledge of God. Let vs then geue him thanckes, ſence that of his mere goodnes, he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>numerat vs among the elect, and praye we him that he geue vs ſo much light of his goodnes, that in euery place and time we mai render him perfecte lande, honoure and glorye, by Iheſu Chriſte oure Lorde.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:4370:54"/>
               <head>¶ If man haue libertie or not and in what maner: the .xiii. Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome myght thinke it ſuperfluous for a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiane, to thynke whether he be fre or not, but that it is inough to force him ſelf to make all poſſible reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence agaynſt euell, and his beſt power to do wel, geuyng al honor &amp; glory to god, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in ſuche a caſe, they walke to god ſurely, neither falling into the depth of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But herein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth the difficultie, in ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing all the glorie to god. Yea it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble that man whyle arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly he preſumeth of hym ſelfe (thinkyng to do that whiche he doth not) can geue al the glory to god. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore haue I iudged it neceſſarye to ſhewe what man can do, to thend y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beyng able to knowe and diſcerne betwene that which in dede is his, and that that is goddes, he can and maye render all prayſe and lande vnto him to whom of duty it belongeth. Fyrſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the beyng of the creatures, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the beyng of god (by beyng infinitely far from the perfeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the diuine eſſence) is but a ſhadowe, yea rather no beynge,<note place="margin">Roma. iiii</note> ſo that truly it may be ſayde that god only is that which is: neuertheleſſe wyth al this,<note place="margin">Exo. iii.</note> it
<pb facs="tcp:4370:55"/>
can not be ſayde but that the creatures haue a beynge, although imperfect, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the diuine. And ſo is it true, that they haue vertue, during the whiche they worke, although principally in the vertue of god.</p>
               <p>Therfore when the Lord had created the world, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the earth to ſprynge, and the waters to bringe forthe. Then falſe is the opinion of them that Imagine that god, &amp; not the ſunne dothe geue lyght, &amp; god not the fyre doth geue heate, and ſo of al the reſte of thinges created, that God dothe worke in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; not the creatures, but euery creature euen to the moſte vile, hath his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per vertue, duringe the whiche, it worketh. True it is, that in the creatures inferiour to man, there is no libertie at all, becauſe that beinge not let, they muſte of neceſſiti worke according to the vertue that thei haue in the diſpoſition of thinges poſſible or ſufferable, directlye ſet before them as it is ſene in bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, and ſo it is neceſſarye, they moue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to theire vertue, ſtrength, and ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, the whiche is ſeene in the waters, that runne to the ſea, nether it is in the power of liuinge ſoules vnreſonable, to moue or not to moue weaklye or ſtronglye, to the obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that they apetite or deſier. Take away the impedimentes, they muſte of neceſſitie moue them ſelues there vnto, after the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:4370:55"/>
of the ſtrength, and apetite they haue. Therfore in them is no libertie at al, as ther is in man, in whome I conſider fiue ſortes of mouinges, and operacions. The firſt are mere natural as if a man ſhuld voluntarely throw himſelf downe, it ſhuld not be in his lybertie to withholde him ſelfe, but ſhulde be by his weighte, compelled lyke a ſtone to diſcende euen to the earthe. True it is, that the ſame faul was in his liberti, in as much as he mighte not haue throwen him ſelfe downe at all. The ſeconde mouinges, that I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are vegitatiue, as the grow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge when they are children, and nuriſhinge and ſuche like, the which alſo doth plantes. And ſpeakynge of thoſe, I ſaye that they are not in the libertie of man, ſauynge that he maye kyll him ſelfe, and depriue him of that lyfe whych the trees can not do.</p>
               <p>The thyrde are operacions animall, as to ſee, heare, and taſte, and ſuche lyke, of the which ſpeakinge, I ſaye, that albeit, it be in the power of man, not to heare a voyce that is preſent wythout cloſinge his eares, and ſo of the other lyke operacions, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it is in hys libertie to ſhut vp thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the preſence of the obiectes or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> delyght hym, &amp; to withdraw hym ſelfe frome them, and ſo not to moue,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:56"/>
or to moue to one ſide or another, ſoftlye or ſtronglie, as he will, the which the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymalles or liuinge ſoules can not do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge neceſſitate, to moue according to theire apetites. But ſpeakinge, of the foure ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racions whiche are humaine, as to thincke one or an other thinge, to ſpeake or not, in this maner or in that, to lerne this or that ſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, to gouerne him ſelfe or others in this waye or in the other, yea not to do, or elſe to do, always more or leſſe, to this or that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (in caſe he haue goods in power) to faſt watch, praye, to heare the word of God, to communicate or not, and ſo of all the other like operacions, I ſaye, that they are in the power of man, that is that men (without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſpecial grace and miracle but only d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the generall influence of God) haue in their power to do them, &amp; alſo not to do them, and alwaies they ſhal do them, if thei effectuouſlye ſhal wil to do them, not being letted of God, or of ſome other ſtronger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they, and ſo alſo ſhall they not do them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge not forced, and not willinge, to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, men are not images. Yea that they are free in thinges humane, it is ſo cleare, that it can not be declared by a rule more knowne, but ſpekeinge of the laſte worckes, that are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſpiritual and deuine, the which are grat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and acceptable to God, as to haue liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:4370:56"/>
lyght, and ſpirituall knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandinge of god, to haue in him fyrme fayth &amp; hope to loue him, honour hym, laud hym, and reuerence hym, with all thy hert, to order all thy lyfe to his glory, to obey and commit hym ſelfe wholy to his gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wyth mortifiyng and deniyng him ſelfe, the fleſhe and his owne prudence, and to loue hys neyghbour as him ſelfe, euen to his ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies for the loue of god, wyth the herte to praye for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and do them all the good poſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble: And finallye to do ſuche workes to the glorie of god is not in the libertie of them that are carnall, &amp; not regenerate by Chriſt, becauſe that it is not in theyr power to haue the ſupernatural knoweledge of god, ſence it is aboue all their myght.</p>
               <p>It is not alſo in theyr power to haue liue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly faythe in god, hope, and charitie, for as muche as they are the gyftes of god, diuine vertues &amp; ſupernatural. Therfore it is not in theyr libertie to honour god in any wyſe as is due to hym, and that thys is true, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue to make experience in them ſelues, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoringe them to haue more knoweledge of god then they haue, to haue in hym grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter faythe and hope, and to loue hym more, and they ſhal perceyue that it wyl not come to effecte: wherof it foloweth that being not
<pb facs="tcp:4370:57"/>
in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of infidels, and not regenerate by Chriſte to loue God with al theire harte no nor aboue al other thinges, that alſo it is not in theire power, not to loue the thinges created, but in Chriſte and by Chriſt, nether is it in theire power, not to loue them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues diſordinatelye, or theire parentes, frin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, dignitie, honoure, goodes, pleaſures, &amp; the reſte of thinges that are to them profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, commodious and delectable, and more ouer it lieth not in theire power, not to hate their enemies, ſo that thou maiſt ſe, how it is in theire power, to loue them ſpeciallye ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituallye in Chriſte: and to the glori of God ſuche like paſſiones and effectes, are not in oure power, as euerye one hath experience continuallye in hym ſelfe.</p>
               <p>A wycked man mighte abſteine frome killinge his enemye, when he mighte do it, yea and do his beſte to healpe him, but it ſhoulde not be in his power, to loue him in his herte, and muche leſſe in Chriſte and to God.</p>
               <p>Therefore all be it, it is in his libertie, not to kylle his enemye, and ſo to do him good, neuertheleſſe it is not in his power, to refraine frome kyllinge hym, or to do hym anye benefite for the glorye of God. The vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlye
<pb facs="tcp:4370:57"/>
mighte, wyth all his conninge and power conſider all thoſe thynges that ſerue to the dyſpraiſe of the worlde, to the morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiynge of theyr ſelues, to the louing of theyr neighbour and alſo God: yet by no meanes ſhould they come to ſuche lyght of the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of God, of theyr owne miſeries and vanitie of the worlde, that they ſhould loue God, to the hate of them ſelues, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayſe of the worlde, as he is bounde to do.</p>
               <p>It is not then in the libertie of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man to do worckes ſpirituall, he hathe neede of the grace of God, of faythe, and knowledge ſupernaturall, nor it is not in hys power to gette, neyther in all nor in parte, anye gyfte of God, grace or ſpiritual vertue. Yea before that by Chriſte he bee regenerate, he can not neyther wyth thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge, deſyringe, or workynge, nor by anye other meanes diſpoſe or prepare hym ſelfe neyther whole nor partelye, to one of the leaſte graces of God: ſo that by thoſe hys thoughtes, deſyres, or worckes, he maye be worthye, or haue in all or in parte deſerued that grace.</p>
               <p>And moreouer I ſaye, that as before hys regeneracion he is vngodlye &amp; wicked, euen ſo is ſin al his thoughtes, deſires, &amp; workes
<pb facs="tcp:4370:58"/>
and this is, bicauſe that while he is carnall, beinge the ſeruaunte of ſinne and concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence whiche reigneth in him, he is deade to God, and aliue to him ſelfe, he nether doth worcke nor can worcke, to the glorye of god as he is bound, for want of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuely light of him, but being as he is carnal &amp; in his owne loue he is moued to worcke, onlye for his owne intereſte, he ſinneth then, not for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge almoſte and like worckes, but for that he doth them not for the glorie of God. And althoughe the vngodly abſteine ſome times from robbinge and killinge, with ſuche like wicked iniquities, yet alwaies he ſinneth (al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though not ſo muche) not in abſteining, but that he abſteineth not for the loue of God as he is bounde to do, but for his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per accompte intereſte and vtilitie. And ſo is it true in carnall man, while he is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, ſinne doth euer reigne,<note place="margin">Rom. viii. Roma. ix. Rom. vii.</note> for that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but ſinne, yea and euer doth ſinne continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye, becauſe that althoughe he abſteine from homicide, thefte and committing ſuch like iniquities, neuertheleſſe he ſinneth euer continually, in leauing behind him the loue of God with all his herte, as he oughte to loue his neighboure as him ſelfe, to worcke for the helth of his neighboure, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of God, as he is bounde, abſteininge for his honoure from all ſinne. Theire ſinnes
<pb facs="tcp:4370:58"/>
are then innumerable, and yet they thincke in confeſſion to number them al beinge then al the worckes of the carnal, ſinne and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye of puniſhmente: ſee howe they can by any meanes be worthi to be rewarded, and howe thei may be true preparacions, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicions to grace? Therfore as a dead man can not raiſe him ſelf, or worcke toward his reſurreccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor he that is not, worcke to his creation, ſo the carnall man, that in Adam is deade,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii. Roma. iiii</note> and as though he were not can not worcke towardes his regeneracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, yea euen as a humane bodye wythout the ſoule can not moue but downewarde, ſo the dead ſoule without the ſpirite &amp; Chriſte, his life, can not lifte him ſelfe vp, but muſte of neceſſitie deſcende euer downe, in regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge his own intereſte.<note place="margin">Ihon. iii.</note> Therfore he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but ſinne, he muſt be borne again to do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſpiritual and holye, and by oure ſelues we can not be regenerate by no meanes, for it is onlye the worcke of God. It is nedeful then that God creatinge in vs a cleane hert do geue vs a new hert,<note place="margin">Pſal. i.</note> as Dauid did praie and God did promiſe bi his prophetes with oute me, ſaithe Chriſt, ye can do nothinge, that is ſpiritual, holi and grateful to God. Chriſte then is wholye our rightuouſnes, &amp; this is the more riche noble and happi righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if we were iuſte bi our ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:59"/>
yea none ſhuld be iuſte, if our iuſtice dyd in any part depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs nor our owne glory excluded,<note place="margin">i. Timo. i Rom. iiii. Deute. viii.</note> as Paul and Moſes wylleth it to be. There are many that thinke that as men choſe to ſerue a Prince, ſo we choſe to ſerue god, but he him ſelfe in the contrary, where he ſayd, you haue not choſen me, but I you. Likewiſe they thinke, as they that beſt ſerue obtein moſt fauour of their lord, &amp; thoſe that haue loſte it, the more they humble them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, the ſoner they recouer it: ſo they thinke of vs with god. Thus they build theyr good lyfe,<note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> not vpon Chriſte, but on them ſelues, and fall frome the diuine grace. And alſo it is clene contrary: for not for that we repent, humble vs, and do good worckes, therfore he geueth vs his grace: but becauſe he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs his grace, therfore we do worckes that are holye. So that, not for that the good thyefe vpon the croſſe dyd confeſſe Chriſt, therfore he dyd illuminate him, but for that Chriſt did illuminate and touch his herte, therfore he dyd confeſſe him: and the lyke happeneth of all vs.</p>
               <p>And what good worke dyd Paule when Chriſt conuerted him? He was moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye agaynſte his honoure, euen as we were before he called vs. Theſe that are not rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, bee wyth Saincte Peter in a darcke
<pb facs="tcp:4370:59"/>
priſon, bounde with manye cheynes, in the power of the Deuyll, a ſlepe in ſinne, and wylte thou that they bee ſaued by them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues? No, the Lorde him ſelfe muſte needes awake hym, the euell tree can not brynge forthe good frute, as Chriſte ſayde,<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> no more canne the vngodlye good worckes. Before wee are by Chriſt regenerate, we are fleſhe, and that whiche ſpryngeth of the fleſhe, is fleſhe.<note place="margin">Iho. iii.</note> Therefore canne we do no ſpirituall worckes, yea euen as Paule ſaythe, all the effectes and deſyres of the fleſhe are death, vncleane are all oure worckes whych pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede of our corrupte nature, and finally he that is not wyth Chriſte, is agaynſte hym.</p>
               <p>God at the beginnynge made man free, but in ſinninge he was made in ſuche ſorte the ſeruaunt of ſinne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not only he can not, neither in all nor in parte, merite before god any grace, but he can not in his lyght do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe but ſinne: yet not for this he ſhuld leaue to heare the worde of God, to praye, to take counſayle, to ſeeke to bee corrected, to do almes and lyke worcke, not for that he dothe deſerue grace but punyſhemente, euen as he that by force is compelled to humble hym ſelfe, and axe pardon of hys enemye, for that fayned humilitye, he meritethe not to bee pardoned, but ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:4370:60"/>
merite ſo muche the more to be puniſhed, as that, hauinge vniuſtli offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him, he ought with his herte, to haue humbled him, and aſked pardon, and hath not done it. Now ſo the vngodlye, in aſkinge mercie of God, do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth ſinne, for he that aſketh not for his glory as he is bounde, but for his owne gaine, nor therfore he ought to ceaſſe from aſking help of God, for that he ſinneth not in prayinge but for the not prayinge in ſpirit, for the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of God, and with al due circumſtances in that caſe he did partlye obey God, for if he did not praye he ſhould ſinne much more greuouſlye. The Zamaritane not onlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued not to haue grace of Chryſte, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him water, but for that her demaund, ſhe deſerued to be puniſhed, bicauſe ſhe did it not in faithe, and to the glorye of God.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe Chriſte would that ſhe ſhuld aſke, and that it ſhulde paſſe by thoſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Now ſo he wil that ſinners aſke grace, and do thoſe worckes that he hath commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded them, albe it thei do them not to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of god, beinge blinde to diuine thinges, yea darckenes it ſelf,<note place="margin">Ihon. x. Ioh. viii.</note> as writeth ſaint Ihon. But after the ſinners are regenerat bi chriſt then as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, thei are free, and not the ſeruauntes of the deuell nor of ſinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that althoughe in them remaineth the concupiſcence of ſinne, neuertheleſſe thy do
<pb facs="tcp:4370:60"/>
not conſente to it, they obey not vnto it.<note place="margin">Roma. vii.</note> It dothe not reigne in them: but they haue ſo much lyght of god, &amp; ſo much ſpirite (which helpeth their infirmitie) that they are ſtirred to the glorie of god,<note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> thoughe not wholy as they wolde, for becauſe of the repugnaunte fleſhe. Therfore ſaid Paul, I do not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good that I wold do,<note place="margin">Rom. vii Pſalm. xxxi. Roma. viii.</note> but the euell that I wolde not. But ſuche defectes are not imputed to them, for that they are by faythe graffed in Chriſte. The regenerate bi Chriſte are prone and readie to the good, god hathe illuſtrate their mind and toutched their herte, in ſuche maner that with all their ſoule, voluntarely frely, and gladly, they do holye worckes, to the glory of god, ſo that as god counſailed the ſoules of them that did electe Dauid to content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in their herte to haue him for their kinge, ſo he moneth the hert of the regenerate, wyllinglye to haue god for theyr god, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit them to his gouernaunce, and to delight to be gouerned of him, with hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe him as a celeſtial father. So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the ſonnes of Adam, before they be regenerate, are the ſeruauntes of ſinne, for that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but ſinne, &amp; therfore becauſe they can not worcke, wyl, deſire, nor ſtyrre in any waye to the glory of god, as they are holden, but only for their carnall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which al men not regenerate, are called fleſhe, not
<pb facs="tcp:4370:61"/>
only the body, but the ſoule, the wyl, deſires and thoughtes, with al the reſt, ſo after that they are regenerate, they be fre from ſinne, (for that they can worke to the glory of god) and are ſeruauntes of ryghteouſnes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although, as concerning the ſubſtaunce and beyng of the bodie and of the ſoule, thei remayne the ſame: neuertheles, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they wer called fleſhly men, and fleſhe, for that they ſought not but theyr owne pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per thynges, afterward they are called ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men and ſpirite, in as muche as they ſeke the glory of God, the which they maye do, for that God hathe geuen them by mere grace liuely lyght and ſpiritual feling, and knowledge of his goodnes, yea duringe in them that perfect light, not only they are fre from ſinne, for that thei be able not to ſinne, but alſo they can not ſinne, for that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but loue god &amp; worke to his glory.</p>
               <p>And this is the perfecte libertie, the beinge fre frome the power to ſinne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge not of power to ſinne, is not to ſinne. Otherwyſe, neither the ſaintes that are in the other lyfe, nor the Aungels ſhoulde bee perfectly fre, neither Chriſt nor god, for thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſinne. It is very true this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſome time doth let his electe &amp; holy men fal, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing his diuine light for a time (yet for their benefites) therfore we are not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:4370:61"/>
and wholy fre from the power to ſinne, as we ſhal be in the life to come, but thei are fre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power to ſinne with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the liuely &amp; actual lyght of god. So then as the carnal, before their regenera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion are in ſuch ſort the ſeruauntes of ſinne, that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but ſinne, not therfore abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutelye &amp; without condicion, but ſo long as they haue not the holy light of god, ſo the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>generate are in lyke maner fre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſinne, yea they can not choſe but worke wel, yet not abſolutely, but during in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that liuelie &amp; actual light of god. And w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al this, neither the wyl of the fleſhe is viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to wyl euel, nor the wyl of the ſpirite to wyl wel. And this is, for that the wyl ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not worke, but of wyl (therfore wyllingly) but if it were poſſible that of any outward pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er it were forced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by that viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, it ſhuld worcke not voluntarilye. And on the other ſyde, it ſhuld worke willingly for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it coulde not worke but of the ſame wil y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhuld worke vnwillingly &amp; willingly the which in a maner is vnpoſſible, &amp; impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and gainſaiyng. So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as if one being a ſlepe were throwen donne from a hyghe place, and in the fallinge ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, perceyuinge hys falle, ſhould wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly contente him ſelfe, and haue pleaſure ſo to fal donne to the botome, when he were
<pb facs="tcp:4370:62"/>
at the ground, he were well worthy to haue ſhame &amp; puniſhement, not for that he might in his fal withhold him ſelfe, for it was not in his choyſe nor libertie, but for that he did ſo delight and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent him ſelf with that fal, with his ful wyl, &amp; would it wyth the herte, in ſuch ſorte, that al beit he myght haue had the power to reſtraine that fal, he wold not haue done it. Euen ſo the lyke beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of al the chyldren of Adam, that beynge fallen in him, although when thei come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeres of diſcreſſion, &amp; begyn to diſcerne the good frome the euel, they perceiue the ſinnes that they do, euery way they do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarilye, delighting therin, ſo that althoughe they be not of power, not to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ar neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les worthy of poniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they in ſorte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit them wyllingly, that if they had pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er not to do them, yet euery waye they wold do them, beinge their wyll ſo malignau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, as it is. Their wyll then is not violented or forced to do euel of ani outward power, but of his owne proper &amp; entiere or inward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce: And ſo the other partie, the regenerate by the gladſome, entier, liuelye, &amp; enflamed light that they haue of the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of god, thei are forced to eleuate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (Therfore volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarily, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect liberti) to god, to whom for euer be all laud, honor, and glory, through Ieſu Chriſt our Lorde, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:4370:62"/>
               <head>¶Of the effectes wrought bi the ſpirite of god when it entreche in to the ſoule: the .xiiii. Sermon</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as Chriſt entring into the holye citye of Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Math. xxi</note> the whole citie was moued, ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth the citie of the ſoule when Chriſte entreth therein, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ſence from that as from a fort &amp; ſtrong municioned rocke he hath the greate deuyll to chaſe away. And if in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lunatike ſon,<note place="margin">Luke. xi. Luke. ix</note> ther was a greate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mocion, when Chriſt out of his body wold haue drawen the malignau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpirite that had poſſeſſed hym: thinke what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mocion there is, when he chaſeth hym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule, in the which he dwelleth more wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyngly. And knowe, that it maketh a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion not onli outward in ceremonies, as do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe chriſtianes when it is nere Eaſter, but there is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mocion within the very bowels of the ſoule, and inward parte of the herte, there is nothing that ſo ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perce the ſoule, as doth the ſpirite of god, when it entreth into it by ſpeciall ſlidinge. Not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly it ſpoileth vs of the olde Adam with hys concupiſcence, &amp; doth cloth vs wyth Chriſt,<note place="margin">Roma. xlii. Ihon. iii.</note> with all his vertues, but alſo maketh vs to be borne a new, that as if a poore man were ſodenly made an Emperoure, he ſhulde be wholy chaunged, ſo he that of a vile ſinner,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:63"/>
is made the ſonne of God chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth though<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, effectes, deſires, and wyll, chaungeth frenſhipes, practiſes, wordes, workes, and life, and of humaine, beaſtly, carnall, earthe, and deueliſhe: he becommeth heuenly, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, angelicall, and deuine as did Paul, goinge to Damaſco, when Chriſt did enter his herte.<note place="margin">Actes. ix Pſalm. lxxvi. i. Reg. xi. Math. xii.</note> There was a mutacion, from the righte hande of God. When the ſpirite of the Lorde entreth in a perſon, he is chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into another man, for that dieng to the world, he beginneth to liue to him ſelf. And if when Chriſte did enter in to the temple he purged it from thoſe that bought and ſolde, thincke if when he entreth into the ſpiritual temple, he clenſeth it from euery vnclennes of ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> there reſtith not in it any thinge of dampnacion, he healeth it moſte perfectlye, ſo that if the vncleane woman was healed, at the touche of the hemme of Chriſtes gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt thinke what it is when Chriſt in ſpirite entring in to the ſoule, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with lyuely fayth, imbraceth him who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his. Alſo as when the ſonne beames enter into thy houſe, thou perceiuiſt in the ayre, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſmaleſt mote which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not ſe before, ſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſoule do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beames of lyght of the diuine grace, the ſinnes are perceiued in more cleare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.<note place="margin">Luke. xv.</note> Yea, as the prodigal ſonne neuer knew nor perceiued truly his own errour, til with
<pb facs="tcp:4370:63"/>
ſuch pitie he was imbraced of his father, &amp; had profe how great was the fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and charitie whiche he had offended: ſo the ſinner when he conuerteth &amp; beginneth with the ſpirite to taſte the diuine goodnes, he beginneth alſo to know his malice, pride, and ingratitude with the reſt his vnlawful ſinnes.<note place="margin">Luke. xvi.</note> He reſtoreth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Zacheus that which is not his, if Chriſt enter into his houſe and diſpenſeth the ſuperfluous thinges, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ryche with the treaſures of Chriſte, he leaueth al with vnmeaſurable loue. He can not participate or take parte of the bountie of god that doth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate &amp; diſtribute to others. The liuelye flame muſte needes breake forth,<note place="margin">Iho. vii.</note> or els beinge ſmoudered it que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth &amp; the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuallye receiue ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning water muſt of force ouerflow: ſo thei that haue in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt,<note place="margin">Roma. viii.</note> by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> teſtimonie wherof they are ſure to be the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of god, haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually one ſuch &amp; ſo entire, ſincere, and pure gladnes (whiche groweth of the liuely knowledge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue of the greate goodnes of god) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not expreſſe it,<note place="margin">i. Pet. i.</note> nor thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes. Therfore not being able to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, they ſpringe &amp; leape for ioye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ihon Baptiſt,<note place="margin">Luke. i.</note> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they make exclamacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Exo. iiii. Acte. iiii. Math. vii.</note> &amp; as to Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſo are their to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges loſed: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> although in praiſing of god thei perceiue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Moſes that they ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer and are of an vnlearned tonge,
<pb facs="tcp:4370:64"/>
neuertheles with the Apoſtels,<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> they can not kepe ſcilence of that which they haue heard, ſene, &amp; felt, with the ſpieite, they muſt nedes ſpeake by the ſuperabundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of loue, that they haue,<note place="margin">Ihon. iiii</note> they deſyre with the woman of Samarye, that euery one ſhould taſte that which they them ſelues haue had experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of. And although for preaching the goſpell they be perſecuted, for al that they do not de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſte and leaue of, but triumphing in al, they perſeuer and go furth euen to the death,<note place="margin">Roma. v.</note> thei feele in ſuch ſorte in the herte the charitie of god,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cte. v.</note> that not onlie it is ſwete to them to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his loue, but with the apoſtels they reioyce therin. And for that they participate of that greate charitie of Chriſte, by beynge his members. Therfore with hym they par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don al men, beyng ready to ſhed their bloud and put theyr lyfe for their enemies, &amp; with Paul alſo to be accurſed from Chriſte.<note place="margin">Roma. ix. Acte. vii.</note> And this, becauſe that as to Steuen, ſo the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens are opened to them, in ſuche ſorte, that in ſpirite with clere &amp; ſupernatural lyght of fayth, they ſee the glory of god, in hauing ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dearely beloued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne for them vpon the croſſe, they reſt alſo quiet as the ſhyp when Chriſt entred into it, they haue the peace of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, knowyng with certeine fayth,<note place="margin">Mat. vi Roma. v.</note> that god by Chriſte &amp; by hys mercie, hath pardoned them. They haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4370:64"/>
quietnes of minde, in ſuche maner, that thoughe they were in al the perils &amp; neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the world, yet alwayes aprouing for iuſte, the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of god, knowyng that he is their only father, that he hath moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler cure of them, &amp; that euery thynge ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them to ſaluacion, they ſtand moſt ſuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, quiet, in peace, &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quillitie. Theſe ſuche for that they walke according to the vocaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of god, haue honour of euery enterpriſe that they take in hand, they can not be letted or reſiſted, no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god. Yea it is force that euerye one feare them, as Herode fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Sainte Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptiſte,<note place="margin">Gene. xxi. Gene. xxvi.</note> for that he had in him the ſpirit of the Lorde, &amp; as Abimelech did Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Iſaac. They are daylye more firme &amp; ſtablyſhed in good purpoſes to do euer better, beyng lyfted vp co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to a greater perfeccion with Paule, althoughe their minde be conuerſaunt in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, deſcending by chriſtian pitie,<note place="margin">i Cor i.</note> to fele the miſeries of their brethern, they laboure alſo to drawe them to Chriſt, and moue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue the ſpirite, &amp; to be in veritie Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes, &amp; not I pocrites. As y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very grape doth moue the birdes to taſte therof, and not the pytfal. And finally, although with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelles, they euer remaine wyth Chriſte and wyth the Cananite,<note place="margin">Ihon. vi. Math. vii.</note> whiche woulde not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte for his vngentle wordes, neuertheles
<pb facs="tcp:4370:65"/>
they are promte and readie for his honoure and glorye, to leaue wyth the Samaritane hys ſwete preſence.</p>
               <p>And what is more to be ſayde when the ſpirite of God dothe enter in to a ſoule, he ſuffereth it not to ſlepe,<note place="margin">Ioh. iiii.</note> nor ſtand in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but maketh it worcke thynges merueylous and inexplicable, for the loue of God: to whome be euer all laude, honoure and glorie by Ieſu Chriſte oure Lord Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Day dwellynge ouer Alderſgate, &amp; Wylliam Seres, dwellyng in Peter Colledge.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4370:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
